<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="pretty-atom-feed.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Ryan Robinson Theology</title>
  <subtitle>Ryan Robinson writes about theology: God, the church, the world, and whatever else he feels like that day.</subtitle>
  <link href="https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/feed/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/" />
  <updated>2025-03-16T10:00:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Ryan Robinson</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Whose Armour?</title>
    <link href="https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2025/whose-armour/" />
    <updated>2025-03-16T10:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2025/whose-armour/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;scripture-text&quot;&gt;Scripture Text&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biblegateway.com/passage/?search=ephesians%206%3A10-24&amp;amp;version=CEB&quot;&gt;Ephesians 6:10-24 (CEB)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/QAIfTCdJlS8?si=oz_Wl48kiJrAnGNo&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; referrerpolicy=&quot;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;transcript&quot;&gt;Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&#39;ve reached the end of this series on Ephesians. We&#39;ve covered some big topics like salvation, diversity in unity, new creation, and a liberatory reading of the household code that invited us into an empowered mutual servanthood. Somehow, despite some of those themes of diversity and liberation, the team we managed to assemble for this series were five white men.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-call-to-fight&quot;&gt;The Call to Fight&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That does put us in positions of relative privilege, as the ones who benefit in the short-term from unjust systems. A very privileged interpretation of this text might be one that is about dominating through force or coercion, that this is about how we need to fight to establish ourselves and protect our people against those other people. It&#39;s about being tough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or at the very least, maybe it&#39;s &amp;quot;spiritual warfare&amp;quot; which for me mostly makes me think of an episode in &lt;em&gt;Xena Warrior Princess&lt;/em&gt;. Xena and Gabrielle are recruited into a battle between angels and demons and there&#39;s lots of flying around and sword fighting and it was really cool to teenage Ryan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is still a strong contingent of the Christian tradition that would say things like that, even though it is hard to reconcile with Jesus. It is also hard to reconcile with this text, which quickly establishes that our battle is not against human enemies. That idea falls apart even faster within the context of the rest of the letter spending so much time talking about things like reconciliation between groups that don&#39;t get along. It&#39;s clearly not about one group needing to dominate the other. Let&#39;s quickly discard that framework, because it doesn&#39;t really deserve any more attention than that. &lt;a href=&quot;https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/cult-innocence/&quot;&gt;See a couple of sermons in the Fall&lt;/a&gt; if you do want to engage more with that topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;principalities-and-powers&quot;&gt;Principalities and Powers&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this text does support the idea that we do need to be ready to fight in some sense. We don&#39;t have a battle against human enemies, but we do against what many translations put something like &amp;quot;principalities and powers.&amp;quot; My apologies to the tech team for all the plosive p&#39;s in repeating this phrase. With maybe some exceptions for the charismatic tradition, &amp;quot;principalities and powers&amp;quot; is not language that we normally use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Common English Bible translation instead unpacks that into &amp;quot;rulers, authorities, forces of cosmic darkness, and spiritual powers of evil in the heavens.&amp;quot; That&#39;s doing something interesting, because it essentially includes the two possible ways to understand who the enemies are in this battle. Rulers and authorities suggest earthly human power structures, the ways that we dominate each other. Forces of cosmic darkness and spiritual powers of evil in the heavens suggest something more supernatural. We might use a word like demons. Or it at least suggests something more abstract about our way of living in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ephesians does not say a lot directly about the nature of these powers and principalities. It&#39;s not generally something that was high priority for the original Paul or any of these other authors who wrote later in his name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But they do come up at a higher rate in Ephesians than anywhere else in Paul. According to Clinton Arnold in Ephesians: Power and Magic, Ephesus was seen to be a major centre for magical practice. By &amp;quot;magic&amp;quot; we mean something like: learning the correct speech and actions that allow you to control spiritual forces that would otherwise harm you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to other ancient sources, this claim by Arnold is supported by Acts 19, which describes Paul&#39;s time in Ephesus. That includes encounters with several people who practiced this kind of magic and then repented by burning all their very valuable magical texts. Acts attributes more demons to Ephesus than anywhere else in Paul&#39;s journeys.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That may be why Paul talks about these powers and principalities more in Ephesians than anywhere else. As is always true with reading these letters, they have a context with specific things the audience was thinking about and that the author was trying to address.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that&#39;s one half of what we saw in the CEB translation, the demon half. And there is a good argument that this is all that Paul meant here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most modern interpreters don&#39;t like reducing it to only be about that, though, for a few reasons:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There&#39;s the modernist bias, that we often start with a presupposition that there is no evidence to believe that such demons exist. If the text is only about those, and we dismiss those, it doesn&#39;t leave us with anything else that it says.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There&#39;s the practical pastoral concern that it can create a scenario of being so focused on these spiritual forces battling out there, it&#39;s easy to ignore what&#39;s happening right in front of you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The one that is most compelling to me: there are plenty of other biblical texts and extra-biblical texts from the same time and even a couple centuries earlier that suggest these two ideas can go together, not be contradictory. These often align the imagery of these spiritual forces with systemic injustices or more broadly the battle between good ways of being in relationship and bad ways of being in relationship. Even within this text, it goes on to explain that the weapons and armour for defeating these evil forces are things like truth, peace, salvation, justice, and the word of God. If it were strictly talking about evil demons, you might expect more &amp;quot;magical&amp;quot; tools like prayer, fasting, maybe some charismatic gifts which Paul isn&#39;t afraid to talk about elsewhere. Also, this text references back to Isaiah which was within a context of being conquered by a literal foreign empire and seeking liberation from that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, there is good reason to believe that it is at least talking about this more abstracted battle between good and bad ways of being, the way of God and the way of the oppressive Empire. Perhaps that&#39;s in addition to literal spiritual forces, but I have a hard time believing that it only meant literal spiritual forces.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Either way, there are a couple more important points here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, evil does exist. It&#39;s true that we can&#39;t neatly divide between the good people and the evil people, like a lot of Xena and other media from when I was a kid. There&#39;s a good argument that this is what the original sin, knowledge of good and evil, meant, that kind of blanket judgement of a person&#39;s value. But that doesn&#39;t deny that evil does exist within many of the ways that the world operates. If you look at the news and we&#39;re being honest, it probably won&#39;t take you that long to find something happening that you want to describe as evil. We know that evil exists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;gods-victory&quot;&gt;God&#39;s Victory&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To paraphrase something from G.K. Chesterton, which I believe I first encountered through Rachel Held Evans: the reason we tell fairytales is not to teach children that dragons exist. Children know soon enough that dragons exist, that the world can be scary, that evil happens. The reason we tell fairytales is to teach children that the dragons can be defeated. That&#39;s a big part of what I think is happening here in Ephesians. They knew the evil existed; what they needed to know was that it could be defeated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The recipients of the letter were told they didn&#39;t need to be afraid of these evil powers anymore. They didn&#39;t need to be constantly resorting to their own magical efforts to try to contain them, because God already won.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This motif of Jesus defeating evil as well as death is a common one throughout the Pauline letters, as well as other texts like Revelation and Jesus&#39; casting out demons in the Gospels. In the Adult Ed today, we&#39;ll look a bit at some other motifs in the New Testament for explaining exactly what was accomplished by Jesus&#39; life, death, and resurrection. This is the most prominent one: that somehow Jesus defeated evil and death.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I haven&#39;t completely dropped social media this year for Lent as I often have in the past, but I have tried to maintain stricter limits. I&#39;m trying to find that balance of staying informed without being overwhelmed. That does mean that some days with how fast the news is changing that I miss about 6 stages of commentary on new tariffs, then counter tariffs, then a reversal of part of a tariff, then a delay of one tariff but another one added, then a reversal of part of the reversal from earlier in the day, and I&#39;m very tired of the word tariff even with less social media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the ways that I do feel overwhelmed when I spend too much time on social media soaking up every bit of bad news is that I want to know what I can do to defeat these evils. I want to jump to fixing the problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That gets me closer to the Ephesians&#39; magical approach. They were trying to constrain evil through their own efforts, as I am often tempted to do. The message that they needed to hear was one of transcendent hope and grace. They were told to be confident in God&#39;s victory. It might not always look like it, but the victory is assured. It wasn&#39;t solely their job to defeat evil through sheer effort, with the right magical words or actions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found myself thinking that this is the main message I needed to hear from the letter, too: I, alone, raging against the darkness, cannot fix everything. Fortunately, I am not alone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This God does not sit back and wish us good luck defeating evil. This God has led the charge into the darkness. This God is one who entered the trenches, who has defeated evil and is defeating evil.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-gods-armour&quot;&gt;How: God&#39;s Armour&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This passage is often referred to as the &amp;quot;armour of God&amp;quot; and that leaves upon a couple of possibilities for how to interpret the preposition &amp;quot;of.&amp;quot; Tom Yoder Neufeld unpacks this well in his commentary. He argues that it is a mistake to believe that it is God giving us necessary protection for our battles, like God is just the blacksmith. Instead, this is God&#39;s armour, the mechanisms by which God fights. This text, first and foremost, is saying what God is like and has done, summarizing a letter which has largely been about what God has done.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I thought it was interesting in Marcus&#39; message a few weeks ago when he mentioned how Paul and those others who wrote in his name get cast as legalistic. I&#39;ve heard that version, that Paul is all about the harsh rules that we must follow. Therefore, they conclude, we need to dismiss him and everything he wrote. I&#39;ve also heard the version that Paul is obsessed with a cheap empty version of grace, that God has already forgiven us no matter what we&#39;ve done to hurt each other, so don&#39;t worry about things like social injustices that we are participating in. Therefore, Paul does not adequately prepare us to be capable of things like apologizing or learning to love people better. In conclusion, we should dismiss him and everything that he wrote. We&#39;ve got one big chunk of people upset at Paul for one idea and another big chunk upset at Paul for the complete opposite idea.
I think those two extremes are missing that there is a third option. According to this text, the battle is fought by &amp;quot;putting on&amp;quot; this new reality, this new way of being that was revealed most fully in Jesus. We are invited to inhabit the way of God, participating in God&#39;s battle with God&#39;s armour. This aligns with much of the other language of Ephesians to this point, about being the new creation in Christ. We don&#39;t fight our own battle through our own magical efforts, essentially the legalistic reading of Paul. We don&#39;t sit back and pretend there isn&#39;t a battle either, which is essentially the cheap grace reading of Paul.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each piece of armour, what God&#39;s new way of being looks like, could be its own sermon. These are big ideas: truth, peace, justice, and the word of God. We don&#39;t have time for that. Believe me, I was ready to give a rant on the concept of truth in the disinformation social media age. You&#39;ve been spared from that with the time limits on these sermons, which I am pushing close to, so it is time to wrap up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main takeaway is that the church is called to a way of being that follows God&#39;s lead and stands in contrast to the powers. Where the powers use misinformation and disinformation to amass wealth and influence, God is truthful and calls the church to be truthful. Where the powers seek to divide and incite violence, God reconciles humanity and calls the church to be peacemakers. Where the world accepts injustice if it benefits them, God seeks justice for the most marginalized, even at cost to themself on the cross, and calls the church to do the same. This is who God is, that is how God defeats evil, and that is what we are invited to put on as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;books&quot;&gt;Books&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Florer-Bixler, M. (2021). &lt;em&gt;How to have an enemy : righteous anger and the work of peace&lt;/em&gt;. Herald Press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have referenced this book multiple times before. It is very good at acknowledging that we do have enemies in the sense that we do have those who are actively opposing what we would consider to be the just way of being in the world, and then looking at how we deal with them in a Jesus-like way. Like I tried to do, it doesn&#39;t accept either extreme framing that there is no battle or that our battle is about dominating others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Du Mez, K. K. (2021). &lt;em&gt;Jesus and John Wayne : how white evangelicals corrupted a faith and fractured a nation&lt;/em&gt;. Liveright Publishing Corporation, a division of W.W. Norton &amp;amp; Company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a historical book that traces the development of the macho violent Christian masculinity imagery over the past century, more relevant to some discussion of the call to fight version of Christianity that I largely cut out from the sermon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arnold, C. E. (1989). &lt;em&gt;Ephesians, power and magic : the concept of power in Ephesians in light of its historical setting&lt;/em&gt;. Cambridge University Press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was the most academic commentary that I went through. It is largely focused on what the &amp;quot;powers and principalities&amp;quot; were in the Ephesians context – how they likely understood these spiritual forces as well as gods like Ephesian Artemis – and what &amp;quot;Paul&amp;quot; was saying about Jesus&#39; victory over them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neufeld, T. Y. (2002). &lt;em&gt;Ephesians&lt;/em&gt;. Herald Press.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tom Yoder Neufeld&#39;s commentary also covers the whole letter, but from an explicitly Anabaptist perspective. There were a couple of key points that came up in his discussion of the &amp;quot;God&#39;s Armour&amp;quot; section which I used in the sermon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;videos&quot;&gt;Videos&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For more on Artemis of Ephesus, here&#39;s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=y9IF4vE9UGE&quot;&gt;a good video from Religion for Breakfast&lt;/a&gt;. That doesn&#39;t impact much about how we read Ephesians, but it is interesting as part of the setting where her worship was quite possibly part of what was meant within &amp;quot;powers and principalities&amp;quot; (the Clinton Arnold book cited above also discussed her place in Ephesian religion).&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Lectionary Notes: Mar 2, 2025</title>
    <link href="https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2025/lectionary-mar2/" />
    <updated>2025-03-01T11:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2025/lectionary-mar2/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been invited to join a group spanning a few churches to share reactions to the lectionary text for the week. Here are my notes going into our final week, Transfiguration Sunday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-texts&quot;&gt;The Texts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lectionary.library.vanderbilt.edu/texts/?y=384&amp;amp;z=e&amp;amp;d=23&quot;&gt;Here are the texts&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This one felt more like the same themes throughout all of them, rather than a progression from one text to the next, so I&#39;m going to structure my notes that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;mountains&quot;&gt;Mountains&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interesting that the encounters with God happen on a mountain each time. It wasn&#39;t unusual in the ancient world to see mountains as liminal spaces, where the gods could more easily meet with humans. Mountains also had practical advantages as the best places to build a city: easier to defend from attackers, easier to have waste water flow downhill away from drinking supplies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe we could argue there&#39;s still some sense that &amp;quot;mountains as liminal space&amp;quot; is true because being on a mountain evokes awe at creation which can make you feel closer to God, but I&#39;m not going to read too much more into it than that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;shining&quot;&gt;Shining&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I love the idea of faces literally shining after encountering God. Jesus is shining in the Transfiguration. Moses shines without even realizing it after talking with God and receiving the commands. Corinthians doesn&#39;t reference shining but does promise transformation in other ways: real freedom, not losing heart, sticking to the truth and conscience.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;veils&quot;&gt;Veils&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, Moses&#39; face shone so much that he had to put a veil over his face. He had to be an intermediary between the Israelites and God because the glory of God was scary to the Israelites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Corinthians uses the veil language a slightly different way. After referencing how Moses needed a veil to keep people from looking directly at God&#39;s glory, he claims that whenever Moses is read, there is still a veil over their minds. In contrast, when one turns to the Lord, the veil is removed and now we see the glory of the Lord as if through a mirror, a perfect reflection. By seeing that perfect image of God, we also become more transformed into that image.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The veiled message through Moses wasn&#39;t wrong. But it was a little bit blurry, veiled for a people who weren&#39;t quite ready for it. Now in Jesus we can see more clearly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is some potential for antisemitism in the veil idea, if we equate &amp;quot;in Jesus we think we see God more clearly&amp;quot; as &amp;quot;Jewish people are inferior.&amp;quot; There isn&#39;t a logical reason why the former would lead to the latter, but it is pretty common in our culture to take a lot of our sense of worth from being right about something, especially the big worldview-shaping things like religious belief. We can simply and humbly acknowledge that the Christian tradition thinks Jesus is the clear revelation of God. It&#39;s fine that Jews and Muslims and Hindus and Buddhists and everyone else disagrees. That doesn&#39;t make us superior to them. There&#39;s no reason why difference has to mean hierarchy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;continuity&quot;&gt;Continuity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the essential counter in these texts to some of the antisemitism risk is that Jesus is within a long line of Jews who encountered God. We get the Moses story, shining so brightly that others couldn&#39;t look at him. The psalm references Moses, Aaron, and Samuel. Corinthians mentions Moses. And Luke mentions Moses and Elijah. There is a sense that Jesus is the fullest revelation of God, but that is firmly coming within the continuity of the Jewish tradition, not discarding that tradition at all.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Lectionary Notes: Feb 23, 2025</title>
    <link href="https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2025/lectionary-feb23/" />
    <updated>2025-02-23T13:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2025/lectionary-feb23/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve joined a group spanning a few churches to share reactions to the lectionary text for the week. Here are my notes going into February 23, 2025, the seventh Sunday after Epiphany.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-texts&quot;&gt;The Texts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lectionary.library.vanderbilt.edu/texts/?y=384&amp;amp;z=e&amp;amp;d=20&quot;&gt;Here are the texts&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;genesis-45-3-11-15&quot;&gt;Genesis 45:3-11, 15&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This picks up at the (mostly) happy ending of the story. At this point, Joseph reveals himself to his brothers, says something that sounds like forgiveness of what they did to him selling him as a slave into Egypt, and declares how even though they meant harm God worked it out for the good of everyone. He promises to provide for them during the famine and kisses them and wept. That&#39;s a pretty powerful story of reunion, reconciliation, and God working even through evil to bring about a good outcome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But if you read the few chapters before this, starting at chapter 42, Joseph did a lot of torturing his brothers before this big moment of forgiveness. Most of the brothers, all but Benjamin, first come to Egypt to buy food because there&#39;s a famine and only Egypt stockpiled enough food (thanks to Joseph&#39;s interpretation of dreams). They meet Joseph but don&#39;t recognize him, having assumed he died a long time ago or at least was still a slave. He recognizes them, accuses them of being spies, and says that the rest of them will stay in prison until one of them goes back and gets Benjamin, which somehow will prove that they&#39;re not spies. He put them all in prison for 3 days, then softens the offer to only making Simeon stay. Then he puts the silver which the brothers had used to buy the food back into their sacks so that they will panic when they see it, knowing that they will be accused of theft.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The brothers (other than Simeon) get back to Jacob and tell them they need to take Benjamin this time. They get back to Egypt with everything they have to offer, including a lot more silver, and immediately explain how they got their silver back on the previous trip. Joseph says that&#39;s fine, serves them a giant dinner, and then does the same thing again: sends them on their way but with their silver returned quietly to their bags. That sounds generous. But this time instead of letting them go, he immediately sends somebody to catch them, accuse them of theft, and threaten to make whoever is found to have the silver a slave. That is Benjamin, Jacob&#39;s favourite. Judah knows that this would kill his father Jacob to lose Benjamin and offers to stay instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s when we get to this passage and its happy ending. With the time to travel back and forth between Egypt and Canaan, this would have been months of emotional torture of his brothers and father, and keeping one in prison. There is no apology for any of that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, the big theme here that lines up with other recent weeks and other texts this week: God reverses our power structures. The older brothers meant to harm him, but God took care of him and ultimately put him in a position of power over his brothers where they depended on him. That part is powerful and reassuring in a world where we often feel like we don&#39;t see justice. But in this particular story, there is a lot of cruelty along the way, and on its own it might be too easy to fall into concepts of justice that require extensive punishment before forgiveness is possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;psalm-37-1-11-39-40&quot;&gt;Psalm 37:1-11, 39-40&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It largely has the same themes of the reversal of power, but explicitly without a lot of the retribution first. This is clear that you should not fret because of the wicket, refrain from anger, forsake wrath. In short, we don&#39;t need to seek retribution because God will make sure things are set right. God is our salvation and refuge, not needing to take revenge into our own hands.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-corinthians-15-35-38-42-50&quot;&gt;1 Corinthians 15:35-38, 42,50&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This flows fairly well out of the above theme of the psalm. We trust that God will make things right, not following the logic of the world that demands we take vengeance ourselves. This is supported by the resurrection, where God in Jesus allowed himself to be killed but then came back. This shows that God has power over death and those who seek to wield death. The power reversal happens, but it comes through death which at first seems like it is supporting the existing power. &amp;quot;What you sow does not come to life unless it dies.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;luke-6-27-38&quot;&gt;Luke 6:27-38&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Luke text perhaps makes these themes a bit more practical. While the psalm and Corinthians declare that God will bring salvation from the wicked powers of the world, Luke gets more down-to-earth in what this looks like when you are oppressed by those wicked powers. Rather than only loving those who love you, Jesus commands that we are to also love our enemies, which in that context would have included some brutal Roman oppressors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, there is an interesting three steps of hatred toward you:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Do good to those who hate you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Bless those who curse you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pray for those who mistreat you.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At first, if somebody hates you but isn&#39;t directly harming you, you have some potential to actively do good to them, which will maybe cutting them off from hating you. If it escalates to them actively cursing you, you can actively bless them in return. If they are actively harming you, you probably aren&#39;t in a position anymore to actively seek practical good for them, but you can still pray for them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &amp;quot;turn the other cheek&amp;quot; part is often misinterpreted as encouraging passivity, however. This isn&#39;t accurate. The Matthew version of this text, in 5:38-40, is a bit more clear, as it specifies that if someone slaps you on the right cheek, turn the other cheek as well. What&#39;s the difference? Try to imagine if somebody is looking at you and they&#39;re right-handed as everyone was assumed to be. For them to slap you on your right cheek, they need to backhand you. This part is still mostly true today: a backhand slap is usually a sign of dominating power over someone who think is clearly inferior to you. You don&#39;t backhand someone who is your equal. So when you turn the other cheek, you&#39;re essentially saying &amp;quot;you may have the power to slap me but I&#39;m going to make you look me in the eye and treat me as an equal while you do it.&amp;quot; And that sounds a lot like nonviolent resistance movements in the modern world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is an interesting progression in the order of these texts, which doesn&#39;t always work out that way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Genesis, we see God working for the good despite evil situations, reversing power structures to put the little brother sold into slavery back in a position over his brothers. But he still clearly felt he had to do some major revenge first.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Psalm encourages us to let go of our anger and trust that God will take care of that power reversal without us needing to take revenge.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Corinthians, we see how that parallels the logic of death and resurrection, requiring that we die to self in order to be raised again in God&#39;s new life.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In Luke, Jesus explicitly teaches us to do some of that dying to self by loving those enemies even while they are oppressing us.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Religious Legacy in Kingdom of the Planet of the Apes</title>
    <link href="https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2025/kingdom-planet-apes/" />
    <updated>2025-02-19T16:46:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2025/kingdom-planet-apes/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;One of my favourite movies of 2024 was &lt;em&gt;Kingdom of the Planet of the Apes&lt;/em&gt;, despite it getting mostly just ok reviews. I watched it again recently after picking up the 4K Blu-ray. I love how it handles legacy and the conflict between maintaining a message of peace and those who want to use that brand while furthering the opposite of peace, violent empire building.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;encountering-a-compassionate-caesar&quot;&gt;Encountering a Compassionate Caesar&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For some background, in the previous 3 movies, Caesar was the leader of the apes. He wasn&#39;t perfect, but mostly he managed to unite apes to work together and to not start any fights with humans. Over the course of that trilogy, the power dynamic flipped from humans being dominant and apes just trying to survive to a more equal war and eventually to humans fighting for their survival, but Caesar remained true to his convictions of trying to find a peaceful coexistence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Kingdom&lt;/em&gt; jumps ahead several generations. Our new main character Noa hasn&#39;t even heard of Caesar at first, coming of age happily in his peaceful ape community living harmoniously in nature. But then his community is attacked and taken away and he must set out to save them. During the attack is the first and second time we hear &amp;quot;For Caesar&amp;quot; as a clear battle cry of the attacking apes. They clearly see what they are doing as part of the legacy of Caesar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He then meets Raka, who is very much styled after a priest, with a stole and a pendant with a religious-like symbol on it. Raka explains that his work has been to protect the real legacy of Caesar. He declares that the attackers are shameful to misuse Caesar&#39;s name and how it is sad that so few remember the true Caesar, with him as the last member of the Order of Caesar. He repeats &amp;quot;Apes together strong&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;ape shall not kill ape,&amp;quot; a couple of Caesar&#39;s main recurring phrases. He explains that humans are slow witted but there was a time when humans and apes lived side by side, during the time of Caesar, and they were important to Caesar, so he will do his best to be compassionate to them as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They see a human (played by Freya Allen) near Noa&#39;s horse and Noa tries to scare her away, but Raka says that she is not a threat. Raka then decides to join Noa on his journey because the human is following Noa, which intrigues Raka. Raka is kind to the human, sharing food and warmth while encouraging mercy. He names her Nova, the name for all humans, although he doesn&#39;t know why, just that it has been that way since Caesar&#39;s time (that happened in the previous movie, &lt;em&gt;War&lt;/em&gt;). He explains how Caesar cared so much for humans, leading with decency, morality, compassion. Noa is skeptical but plays along, then starts to realize that she is smart and develops some compassion for her because she reacts to looking through a telescope the same way he does. They decide to share a horse so she can come with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They encounter a &amp;quot;herd&amp;quot; of other humans, who don&#39;t have the intelligence of Nova, but they are then attacked by the same mysterious group who attacked Noa&#39;s community earlier. Noa saves Nova, but in the process Nova reveals that she can speak.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few scenes of bonding later, Raka sacrifices himself to save Nova whose real name we have now learned is Mae, and as he is about to die he says &amp;quot;together strong.&amp;quot; Not &amp;quot;ape together strong,&amp;quot; just &amp;quot;together strong.&amp;quot; He is modifying Caesars words but to maintain Caesars teaching about compassion for humans. That is a fascinating insight into healthy religion: cling to the love message that matters and be a little loose with specific phrases. Some branches of religious traditions get that backwards.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;proximus-and-empire&quot;&gt;Proximus and Empire&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Noa and Mae are captured by the violent group of apes and we start to see how their interpretation of Caesar is extremely different. They are assembling an Empire. Proximus, their leader, gets a lot of his inspiration learning about Ancient Roman history. They interpret &amp;quot;apes together strong&amp;quot; in a much more fascist way: that they must force all apes to work together over and against humans. It&#39;s not about strength in diverse unity. It&#39;s about strength through dominant uniformity with one clear ape in charge.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This part also has &lt;a href=&quot;https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2021/many-tongues/&quot;&gt;some major Tower of Babel vibes&lt;/a&gt;. Apes from all kinds of diverse communities are forced to work together against their will to further the power of their new Caesar, Proximus, just as the slaves building Babel were forced to work for that empire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The way this oppressive oppressive kingdom is ultimately broken down is also like the Babel story: they embrace their diverse roots; they do not accept that they are only ape slaves to Proximus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proximus talks about the need for evolution, to become even stronger, more dominant over others. He refers to &amp;quot;my kingdom&amp;quot; which is the kind of sense of ownership over other apes that Caesar never showed. The contrast couldn&#39;t get much stronger.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-christian-allegory&quot;&gt;The Christian Allegory&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This all seemed like a pretty obvious allegory of Christianity, or for that matter, pretty much any religion or tradition that has ever had the opportunity to hold power over others. There will be some who declare that their religion requires them to dominate others, to enforce uniformity, to put themselves in charge for the good of everyone. Even if all of that explicitly goes against the teachings of their founder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there are also those like Raka, those who are determined to maintain the peaceful vision of their founder, who encourage compassion toward those who are different and celebrates diversity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have a choice which mode of maintaining our tradition we advance.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Lectionary Notes: Feb 16, 2025</title>
    <link href="https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2025/lectionary-feb16/" />
    <updated>2025-02-15T11:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2025/lectionary-feb16/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve joined a group spanning a few churches  to share reactions to the lectionary text for the week. Here are my notes going into February 16, 2025, the sixth Sunday after Epiphany.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-texts&quot;&gt;The Texts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lectionary.library.vanderbilt.edu/texts/?y=384&amp;amp;z=e&amp;amp;d=19&quot;&gt;Here are the texts&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m not going to do each text separately as I have the past few weeks, because there isn&#39;t a lot unique between them jumping out at me. There are a couple major themes, though.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;trust-and-wealth&quot;&gt;Trust and Wealth&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A theme in all four texts is to trust in God, not in the ways of the wicked. The Luke text at least partially equates &amp;quot;the wicked&amp;quot; with &amp;quot;the rich.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They each tackle that we have some drive, maybe naturally and/or maybe fueled by the advice of those wicked systems and individuals, trying to convince us that we will be satisfied if we pursue wealth for ourselves. We just need to climb to the top of the social hierarchy and then everything will be fine. Not for the people we have to climb over, of course, but let&#39;s not think about them - let&#39;s focus on me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Jeremiah says that this leads to being like a shrub in the desert, not seeing relief, unlike those who trust in the LORD who will continue to bear fruit and not be anxious. Psalm 1 emphasizes that the wicked will be driven away by the wind, while again those who delight in God will yield fruit and not wither. Those are very similar metaphors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1 Corinthians starts to tie this into the resurrection. If that hope of trusting in God is only in life, it is futile. It is obvious that if we are judging only by short-term material wealth and social power, the way of Jesus is pretty naive and ineffective. But if we believe that there is a longer arc of history than that, that there is resurrection, the hope is valid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Luke most explicitly ties this into wealth, sending woe on the rich and blessings on the poor. Matthew&#39;s version of this in the Sermon on the Mount is a bit more abstracted, about the &amp;quot;poor in spirit&amp;quot; without the accompanying woe on the rich, but Luke is more direct to the point. If you prioritize wealth and people speaking well of you, you might get it in the short term, but that&#39;s the entire reward. It&#39;s an Ebenezer Scrooge situation, where you get your wealth for now but you are miserable and have no meaning beyond that. &amp;quot;You have received your consolation.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;hope-for-justice&quot;&gt;Hope for Justice&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another related theme that is present here is that 3 out of the 4 texts (not really the Corinthians one) clearly displays some desire to see negative consequences for those who are doing evil. This is often not a popular position among more privileged &amp;quot;liberal&amp;quot; communities who often want to get rid of any language like that entirely, since it sounds too close to the vindictive god held by more conservative communities who are also often privileged in other ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I don&#39;t think justice and vindictive punishment need to be the same thing. When you have been truly mistreated, especially on a systemic level, it is absolutely normal and in my opinion correct to wish to see consequences - the &amp;quot;woe&amp;quot; that Jesus promises - on those who are hurting you. That doesn&#39;t need to be violent gleeful punishment, but we should be able to acknowledge that something is wrong with this picture and something needs to be done to change it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To bring in the Corinthians a bit less directly, what if God&#39;s justice looks like the death and resurrection of Jesus. It was not justice that killed Jesus. It was profoundly unjust, with those in power deciding to shut down somebody who challenged their power, even though he had not done anything provably illegal to justify a death penalty even by the laws of the time. And yet, if we believe Jesus was the incarnate God who chose that willingly and then was brought back to life? That changes how we think about justice. It isn&#39;t about hurting for the sake of hurting the Romans who killed Jesus, but it does expose and overcome the injustice they committed. God&#39;s power is greater than that injustice and greater than death, which is often the implicit or explicit threat of those carrying out the injustice. If those acting unjustly no longer have the power of death to threaten you, they have no real power over you at all. Real justice requires exposing their injustice. At best, maybe they learn from the consequences of their injustice being exposed and they repent (turn around to a more just way of being).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s the difference between retributive justice, seeking to punish for the sake of punishing, and restorative justice, seeking to make the world whole again (including the oppressors if they will accept it). Being critical of retributive justice is great, but don&#39;t replace that with &amp;quot;well I guess there is no justice.&amp;quot; Instead, try to imagine a restored world, where the oppression is stopped and hopefully the oppressor learns after experiencing those negative consequences to not try it again.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Lectionary Notes: Feb 9, 2025</title>
    <link href="https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2025/lectionary-feb9/" />
    <updated>2025-02-08T11:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2025/lectionary-feb9/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve joined a group spanning a few churches to share reactions to the lectionary text for the week. Here are my notes going into February 9, 2025, the fifth Sunday after Epiphany.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-texts&quot;&gt;The Texts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lectionary.library.vanderbilt.edu/texts/?z=e&amp;amp;d=18&amp;amp;y=384&quot;&gt;Here are the texts&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;isaiah-6-1-13&quot;&gt;Isaiah 6:1-13&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the second week in a row, we get a prophetic call story. This time it is Isaiah and it is more poetic, but the key points are the same: God is holy, the prophet is unworthy, God offers some kind of healing or purification that convinces the prophet to proclaim coming destruction. Even though Isaiah, unlike Jeremiah, is mostly seen as a very hopeful text, that isn&#39;t as obvious in this call narrative.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;psalm-138&quot;&gt;Psalm 138&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is also similar to last week&#39;s Psalm in some of its themes: God is mighty but has special care for those judged to be lowly in human culture, protecting them from their enemies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-corinthians-15-1-11&quot;&gt;1 Corinthians 15:1-11&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Christ died for our sins&amp;quot; definitely has some potential to go down the atonement theory rabbit. Those who believe in penal substitutionary atonement may see this as a prooftext, but it doesn&#39;t actually anything about God&#39;s wrath or justice needing to be satisfied. Even the &amp;quot;for our sins&amp;quot; may be a questionable preposition translation, if I am remembering correctly. I don&#39;t have a good source for that handy, but I believe that is just as easily translated to &amp;quot;because of our sins&amp;quot; which is a simpler cause and effect, not necessarily implying that our sins were placed on Jesus as a scapegoat in order to absorb our penalty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other prooftext rabbit hole it is easy to go down here is apologetics. It cites more than five hundred who witnessed the risen Jesus. That&#39;s not really an airtight apologetics argument since it&#39;s not like we have any way of verifying that those five hundred people really did encounter the risen Jesus and told everyone about it. But that&#39;s not really a focus in this text either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More to the point of this text is in line with the prophetic call narratives of these past two weeks and the psalms of the past two weeks. Paul is emphasizing that he is not that significant, the last to see the risen Christ, the least of the apostles, unfit to be called an apostle, etc. But because of God&#39;s grace toward those who are not worthy, he now is preaching that grace to others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;luke-5-1-11&quot;&gt;Luke 5:1-11&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is one of those Jesus stories that seem a little silly at first. They&#39;ve been fishing all night, not catching much, and Jesus comes along and tells them to put their nets a few feet away on the other side of the boat. Seriously, why would moving the net that small distance go from catching nothing to being completely full immediately, enough that the boat starts to sink. And that&#39;s how Simon (Peter), James and John were recruited to become disciples.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It carries some of the themes from the other texts: they aren&#39;t particularly worthy. They can&#39;t even catch fish on their own, which is their whole job. Simon Peter declares that he is too sinful to be worthy of joining Jesus. Jesus reassures them to not be afraid and to join him despite their &amp;quot;unworthiness.&amp;quot; Then they left everything - all those fish that they had just worked all day trying to catch - in order to take Jesus up on his offer.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Lectionary Notes: Feb 2, 2025</title>
    <link href="https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2025/lectionary-feb-2/" />
    <updated>2025-02-01T11:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2025/lectionary-feb-2/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve joined a group spanning a few churches (a United, my Mennonite, and another Mennonite - a Unitarian was also invited but they all withdrew late) to share reactions to the lectionary text for the week. Here are my notes going into the second week, February 2, 2025, the fourth Sunday after Epiphany.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-texts&quot;&gt;The Texts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lectionary.library.vanderbilt.edu/texts/?y=384&amp;amp;z=e&amp;amp;d=16&quot;&gt;Here are the texts&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;jeremiah-1-4-10&quot;&gt;Jeremiah 1:4-10&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The calling of Jeremiah follows a fairly standard formula for prophetic calls in Scripture. He says he isn&#39;t worthy and God says &amp;quot;too bad, I&#39;ve empowered you to do it anyway.&amp;quot; This is true of basically all the prophets, except Jonah who is arrogant and thinks he knows better than God, which is part of why Jonah is probably best understood as a satire.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What has God empowered Jeremiah to do? To be &amp;quot;over nations and kingdoms, to pluck up and to pull down, to destroy and to overthrow, to build and to plant.&amp;quot; That&#39;s an interesting mix of building something new/better as well as destroying things that are bad. It&#39;s maybe especially interesting Jeremiah is generally the most depressing prophet, with the most focus on how bad things are and less silver linings of hope than most.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;psalm-71-1-6&quot;&gt;Psalm 71:1-6&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The psalm picks up on similar themes of leaning on God&#39;s strength when you don&#39;t have your own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It also picks up on some of the language of being chosen from birth, if not before it. Some of that &amp;quot;before birth&amp;quot; language does make me a little nervous sometimes since it gets used for anti-abortion rhetoric, but that rhetoric is definitely a stretch of the text to make it fit a certain predetermined argument, so I don&#39;t want to get too hung up on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-corinthians-13-1-13&quot;&gt;1 Corinthians 13:1-13&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a well-known text, with the love portion often read at weddings. There&#39;s a lot of value in that on its own, emphasizing how love is the way that we treat each other well. Love is not the boastful or arrogant dictation of what is best for others, but the patient and kind connecting with the beloved in order to seek their true wellbeing as equals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what&#39;s really interesting when paired with the other texts is the &amp;quot;if I have prophetic powers... but do not have love, I am nothing.&amp;quot; The Jeremiah text sounds like prophecy is pretty great and important. And it is. But it isn&#39;t an end goal in itself. If there isn&#39;t love connected to that, it means nothing that Jeremiah was chosen to do those great things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;luke-4-21-30&quot;&gt;Luke 4:21-30&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the second half of last week&#39;s story, where it really picks up. Last week&#39;s was relatively easy to think it was a nice friendly declaration of liberation, but in the second half, we see the story turn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus has started quoting from Isaiah 61, but then stops before the part promising God&#39;s vengeance, which in their context would have been primarily seen as against the Romans. He declares that the promises of liberation have been fulfilled right then, without mentioning the vengeance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The listeners were then amazed at the &amp;quot;gracious words&amp;quot;, which I can only interpret as surprising grace toward the Romans by leaving that part out since the parts he did say were simply quoting Isaiah. Then they wonder if this is really their local Jesus, the son of Joseph. This is the part where it hit me differently than it ever had before. Normally I hear this preached as them being surprised that this guy they knew could grow up to be such a powerful teacher and healer (they&#39;d already heard what he&#39;d done in Capernaum). That&#39;s a fairly innocent reaction of pride for their local boy all grown up now. But another way to read this, in light of Jesus skipping the part about Roman vengeance, might be more like: &amp;quot;this guy grew up here, poor and oppressed under Roman authority like the rest of us, and he dares to declare this Scripture fulfilled while the Romans are still ruling over us? We&#39;re still waiting for that freedom and for that vengeance!&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus makes what might sound like a topic change, saying no prophet is accepted in his hometown, then tells the story of how Elijah and Elisha went to help foreigners at a time when a lot of Israelites could have really used that help. That&#39;s when they get so enraged they are ready to throw him off a cliff before stopping for an unspoken reason as he passes through them (perhaps because this being a Sabbath, they were not willing to travel farther than the Law allowed).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So... maybe the reason why the prophet is never accepted in their hometown is because the hometown demands that the prophet give them special favour, declare that they are more important and more loved by God than anyone else, declaring that they will win and exact their revenge on their enemies soon? But like Jeremiah, who largely prophesied that Babylon was coming to conquer them, Jesus didn&#39;t do that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A key takeaway for me: real prophetic work is often likely to invoke a lot of anger, especially if those being prophesied to feel betrayed by a prophet who was supposed to be on &amp;quot;their side,&amp;quot; because real prophetic work includes dismantling some of that framework of &amp;quot;sides.&amp;quot; It&#39;s not dismissing the evils of Roman oppression or any other oppressive systems, but it is also rejecting simple violent revenge as the solution to it.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Lectionary Notes: Jan 26, 2025</title>
    <link href="https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2025/lectionary-jan26/" />
    <updated>2025-01-25T11:00:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2025/lectionary-jan26/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been invited to join a group spanning a few churches (a Unitarian, a United, and my Mennonite) to share reactions to the lectionary text for the week. Here are my notes going into the first week, January 26, 2025, the third Sunday after Epiphany.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-texts&quot;&gt;The Texts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lectionary.library.vanderbilt.edu/texts/?y=384&amp;amp;z=e&amp;amp;d=15&quot;&gt;Here are the texts&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;nehemiah-8-1-3-5-6-8-10&quot;&gt;Nehemiah 8:1-3, 5-6, 8-10&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Law needed interpretation. It is not something that is immediately obvious. It takes some community coming together to interpret it together and figure out what it means in a new context. That&#39;s an appropriate idea for this first week coming together with this new group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And this communal interpretation of the Law was perhaps especially necessary as they started to rebuild their society after Exile. They didn&#39;t have a lot of momentum of tradition to fall back on. That&#39;s interesting to think about as our culture has less of a default shared understanding of many of the biblical stories or other aspects of tradition. We had a Christian History university prof at our church recently, and one of the things he said is that he can no longer assume students know even general ideas like &amp;quot;who was Jesus&amp;quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;psalm-19&quot;&gt;Psalm 19&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Law is good and beneficial, bringing joy and wisdom. This reminds me of the 1 Timothy 3:16 text. That comes up fairly often in evangelical circles, but I think they&#39;re largely missing the point. The author there concludes that Scripture is useful. Before we can get into any big theological labels like inerrancy or infallibility, sometimes we need the simpler starting point: it is useful, it has value. It&#39;s not the only thing that has value. The psalm notably starts with how nature itself also proclaims God. But it does have value.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;quot;Hidden faults&amp;quot; also jumped out at me. Sometimes we can&#39;t see how we are hurting ourselves or others, and we need some outside source to help us see. Maybe that&#39;s Scripture, or another source of written wisdom. Maybe that&#39;s the church, or some other person. Maybe it&#39;s a nudging of the Holy Spirit in prayer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;1-corinthians-12-12-31a&quot;&gt;1 Corinthians 12:12-31a&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is certainly another appropriate text for the first week doing a group with multiple churches, as it reminds us of the need for many parts of the body.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One question: how much does this mean that each local community needs a lot of diversity within itself, vs those communities needing to keep connected to other communities and those connections needing to be diverse?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big question, though: where is the balance for those who claim to be part of the Christian tradition but are explicitly rejecting any teaching of Jesus? I&#39;m thinking of white nationalists who will say they are acting for Christianity and then directly say that Jesus was wrong or too woke or whatever other buzzword they&#39;re using now to dismiss it. I&#39;m not talking about people who try and fail sometimes, but those who are actively opposed while still claiming the label as a weapon against others. &lt;a href=&quot;https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/cult-innocence/&quot;&gt;I had a couple sermons on that recently&lt;/a&gt;, so I&#39;m not going to go too deep down that rabbit hole again, but I think it&#39;s the single most defining tension for the church at this moment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another question that you need to be able to ask more within your own specific communities: if one member suffers, we all suffer? Really? How often do we feel like that in our churches, in our very individualistic society? It can be easy for one member to suffer in silence while everyone else goes on their way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;luke-4-14-21&quot;&gt;Luke 4:14-21&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That big question from Corinthians leads into the Luke text. Jesus chose to start his public ministry by declaring liberation to captives, recovery of sight to the blind, freedom for the oppressed, and declaring a Jubilee year which is when all debts are wiped out and economic equality is restored. He notably stops the Isaiah reading, from chapter 61, right before it promises &amp;quot;the day of vengeance of our God,&amp;quot; which might be why in the next part of the story people got mad at him and tried to kill him. As people under the boot of the Roman Empire, they were probably pretty happy with the liberation parts, but then Jesus stops before promising vengeance on those Romans. Maybe more on that next week.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Church and Theological Background</title>
    <link href="https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2025/theological-background/" />
    <updated>2025-01-25T10:30:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2025/theological-background/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&#39;ve been invited to join a group spanning a few churches (a Unitarian, a United, and my Mennonite) to share reactions to the lectionary text for the week. We were asked to give a bit of an introduction of our backgrounds first, which is also appropriate to share here as I slowly rebuild some online theological presence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I grew up in a small rural United Church (that&#39;s United Church of Canada, but if you&#39;re reading this in the US, your United Church of Christ is a fairly close parallel). I tend to describe it as &amp;quot;moderate evangelical.&amp;quot; It was absolutely adamant that the Gospel was penal substitution: that God&#39;s justice demanded violent penalty for sin, so God came as Jesus to be the sacrifice taking on that penalty so we didn&#39;t have to. I solidly reject that now for a lot of reasons. But it was not particularly strict on much else that is now common associated with the word &amp;quot;evangelical&amp;quot;: we had women in leadership, we didn&#39;t affirm same-sex relationships but we were part of a denomination that did and we didn&#39;t see any need to fight over it, and we generally tried to care about people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I left for university, I first went to a Canadian Baptist church, which was mostly in a similar category: strict on penal substitution but would be labelled as &amp;quot;liberal&amp;quot; in today&#39;s climate on some other fronts, like a very strong refugee support ministry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of that time I was adjacent to a lot of more extreme conservative Christianity, from views on gender to sexuality to the Bible and the rest, especially in the early days of the Internet when I started encountering more resources on what being a Christian meant and most of those resources were coming from more extreme perspectives. Some of it I bought into a bit more than others, but it never quite felt right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After undergrad, I did a seminary degree at Queen&#39;s School of Religion, which was officially tied to the United Church but had a lot of instructors from a variety of denominations. During that time I somewhat drifted between checking out a few different churches: most often was a United that was liberal in pretty much any definition but there was also a Free Methodist I really enjoyed going to and several others I checked out. It&#39;s also when I started to appreciate a lot more of the liturgical side of the tradition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All through both of those degrees I had found The Meeting House, which some of you may have heard of either for good reasons in the past or less good reasons more recently. This was my introduction to the Anabaptist tradition and I found myself more and more feeling like that was the best descriptor for how I understood Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got married right after university and we went to The Meeting House when we moved to Toronto. Then we went to The Meeting House when we moved to Hamilton. Then we went to The Meeting House when we moved to Kitchener. Then for a few reasons we decided it was time to try something else, and quickly settled at &lt;a href=&quot;https://rockwaymc.ca&quot;&gt;Rockway Mennonite&lt;/a&gt; where we have been since.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along with the Anabaptist influence, I look heavily toward liberation theologies. I would not normally call myself liberal, at least not without checking what the other person means by it first, since it can mean a lot of things and some of those things apply more than others. I would normally use liberationist instead. Liberal has too much connotation to me of educated white people sitting around and talking about things abstractly without interacting with those who are more oppressed or doing much about that oppression directly, while liberationist is driven by the oppressed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So that&#39;s largely my theological perspective: liberationist Anabaptist with some bits that sound a little evangelical and some liturgical impulses still in there.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Empathetic Imagination</title>
    <link href="https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2025/empathetic-imagination/" />
    <updated>2025-01-02T21:46:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2025/empathetic-imagination/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I heard a phrase recently that has stuck with me: &amp;quot;empathetic imagination.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;movies-and-empathetic-storytelling&quot;&gt;Movies and Empathetic Storytelling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was on a movie podcast, which might not seem like the most obvious spot for a line about empathy that stuck out to me like this. But this podcast, named tongue in cheek The Only Podcast About Movies, is primarily approaching movies from the question of what the movie wants to say about the world. Storytelling is powerful, with movies being one of our greatest mediums at the moment, and one particular way it is powerful is in building empathy for stories that are different than yours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the main reason why I do appreciate good TV and movies so much. I am also interested in technical excellence in directing or acting or effects or any number of other elements of a movie. But primarily, I am interested in movies that tell a good story about people who are different than me in some way learning and growing. I want a movie to help me imagine the world being a little bit different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s also, to jump to a different medium, whey I always play videogames with female characters and with non-human characters when given the choice. I&#39;m a human male in real life and the majority of stories are about people like me. It&#39;s a little bit boring to do that all the time. If I have a chance to try to see the world in a slightly different way, I want to take it. I&#39;m very confused by certain elements of gamer culture that opposes the very existence of female characters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;empathy-and-politics&quot;&gt;Empathy and Politics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The context for the empathetic imagination comment was after the US election, and one of the hosts was lamenting the lack of empathetic imagination that made the result possible. He found it extremely discouraging that so few people could imagine how their voting choices would hurt the most vulnerable around them. I think that&#39;s an important insight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carol Off, in her book &lt;em&gt;At A Loss For Words&lt;/em&gt;, tells a story about speaking to a member of one of Canada&#39;s &amp;quot;freedom convoys.&amp;quot; Off asked what &amp;quot;freedom&amp;quot; meant to this convoy member, who replied something about individual choices to do whatever she wanted. Off asked her about a common phrase, that &amp;quot;my freedom ends where your freedom begins&amp;quot; and the convoy member had no idea what to do with that. She couldn&#39;t understand the concept. Off goes on throughout the book about this fundamental clash through history and the present between those who see the goal as their freedom to hurt and rule over whoever they want, and those who see the goal as an equitable freedom inclusive of everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s a lack of empathetic imagination, a total inability to comprehend that other humans exist and your actions will impact them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The peak time of COVID may have been an ultimate example of this. There was a brief window where it seemed like everyone was on the same page that we need to look after each other because a virus is fundamentally a social problem, especially one that spreads at a rate faster than one new infection per current infection as COVID does (much less so when a significant portion of the population is vaccinated). Then the backlash began, where a significant portion of the population made it clear that they were tired of caring about other people. They talked openly about sacrificing the elderly, disabled, and children for the sake of their &amp;quot;freedom&amp;quot; to go to a crowded bar or whatever else they wanted to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just what is the right political approach to &amp;quot;freedoms&amp;quot; can be complicated. We don&#39;t want a government enforcing tyranny on individuals. But we do want a government that can help remind individuals that we aren&#39;t just individuals - that whether we like it or not, we are in this world and this political entity together. And most importantly, we want a government that is able to understand that one group exercising its freedom may be a taking away of freedom from others. It is never as simple as &amp;quot;freedom&amp;quot; for everyone vs &amp;quot;tyranny&amp;quot; for everyone. But I do think a fundamental requirement for a functional society is some empathetic imagination, letting us wrestle with some of those complicated moments while maintaining understanding of what it will mean to others, particularly those most marginalized. That fundamental requirement is currently lacking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;accessible-web-dev&quot;&gt;Accessible Web Dev&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One more tangent is to tie this idea into my day job, building websites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My previous job was for a small company where I was primarily building small websites and CRM systems for non-profits. It&#39;s important work, I&#39;m glad somebody is doing it, and I still recommend the people there when I encounter someone that could use those services. But there is something inherent to that style of work, constantly bouncing between doing similar jobs for multiple clients as fast as possible in order to not lose money, that gets tiring. A chunk of that may be that there is no time to get deep on technical challenges, but even more I realized after starting my current job: there isn&#39;t any time for empathetic imagination. It&#39;s all about getting through the checklist as fast as possible. That includes when it comes to accessibility, which usually had a bare minimum checklist to clear with some automated tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the first big non-technical things I learned in my current job was working with a blind student consultant, who was able to walk some of us sighted staff through her experiences. Instead of &amp;quot;does this test fail&amp;quot; my question became a lot more of &amp;quot;how does her experience compare to a sighted experience? Is there more we can do to make that equal?&amp;quot; That&#39;s a radically different way of thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blind users may be the biggest focus of website accessibility; since websites are primarily visible, that&#39;s the group most consistently left out if the site is not built well. But that&#39;s not the only group to consider. What if you&#39;re deaf and encounter a video with sound? What if you&#39;re colour-blind, or have low vision? What if you&#39;re brand new to the subject of the site with no knowledge of the jargon, vs those who know exactly what they&#39;re looking for?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I write about some of those more on my tech blog and won&#39;t repeat it all here, but I did want to tie it into the idea of empathetic imagination. I am routinely needing to imagine the experiences of others. It makes me a better developer, and I think it makes me a better person.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Shiphrah, Puah, and Moses</title>
    <link href="https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/shiphrah-puah-moses/" />
    <updated>2024-12-10T19:04:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/shiphrah-puah-moses/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I occasionally think about the contrast of the first two chapters of Exodus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In chapter 1, Shiphrah and Puah were midwives who were ordered to kill Hebrew babies. But they don&#39;t do it, instead claiming Hebrew women gave birth before they could get there. They undermined the system, saving a lot of lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In chapter 2, Moses, raised in palace privilege because of a different bit of quiet courage from another couple women, sees a slaver beating a Hebrew. He gets mad, kills him, then has to go into hiding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The role of privilege here does matter, I think. Moses grew up in the palace. He has probably always been taught that the way to enact change is to wield your strength against those who need to be kept in line. So when he sees an Egyptian beating a Hebrew and gets angry, that&#39;s how he responds: wielding his power violently. Then he is surprised to learn that the Hebrew slaves were not excited by this display of dominance; they are afraid that he&#39;ll do the same to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course Moses eventually becomes the movie-style hero that is the symbol of the Exodus. But first he has to spend an entire generation in exile, surrendering the privilege and domination mindset he had, encountering God, and waiting for the people who were trying to kill him to die off. And in that time, &amp;quot;the Israelites were still groaning&amp;quot; (CEB) in slavery, who maybe could have been helped if he shown some wisdom earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently watched the first Hobbit movie again, and was struck by this bit of Tolkien wisdom about power:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saruman believes that it is only great power that can hold evil in check. But that is not what I have found. I&#39;ve found it is the small things, everyday deeds of ordinary folk that keeps the darkness at bay. Simple acts of kindness and love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s at least one big difference from the Exodus context, and the Hobbit context, compared to my context and likely the context of most readers: unlike Egypt at this time, we live in a democracy. We have more ability to directly oppose evil with freedom of expression. And we definitely need a lot of people in that category, explicitly countering harm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I think we also need the Shiphrahs and the Puahs, those who will quietly throw a stick into the gears of the death machine, saving a lot of lives in the process even if nobody seems to notice.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Preaching</title>
    <link href="https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/preaching/" />
    <updated>2024-12-08T11:46:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/preaching/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently joined &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newleafnetwork.ca/store/postevangelicalpreaching&quot;&gt;a New Leaf Network class on Preaching in a Post-Evangelical World&lt;/a&gt;. I only preach 1-2 times a year, and in &lt;a href=&quot;https://rockwaymc.ca&quot;&gt;a church&lt;/a&gt; that would not typically be described as post-evangelical or any other kind of evangelical, but I still find the topic very interesting and I anticipated correctly that they would still be talking through some relevant questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m not going to recap everything they talked about, but will use it as a launching pad to touch on some of the main considerations I have when I am preaching:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;audience-context&quot;&gt;Audience Context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They talk a lot in the New Leaf class about knowing your audience context. What you say to a mostly privileged church needs to be very different than what you say to a poorer, less educated, or otherwise oppressed church. My church? It&#39;s mostly privileged: not quite all white most weeks, mostly pretty solidly middle class, highly educated, mostly cis and straight, mostly married, mostly able-bodied, average age probably in their 60s. I am also mostly privileged. When I preach at my church, I am speaking from that perspective, as somebody wrestling with using my own privilege well and trying to help others do the same. So I do end up talking about things like systemic racism, or more broadly the need to acknowledge our sin. I wouldn&#39;t do that, or at least not in nearly the same way, with a majority Black or poor church. They know the world is broken; they experience it every day. They don&#39;t need that spoken to them. They probably need a lot more of a reminder of how God is with them in that oppression and we have hope that God will bring justice in all the practical ways to restore them as equal members of society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the weird parts of considering audience context is being published widely to the Internet. When I write something to say, I&#39;m writing it for my context. A lot of others share that context, and I hope if they stumble across it on this site or the church&#39;s site or YouTube that it will help them, and I do believe strongly that in almost all circumstances a church&#39;s sermons should be available publicly as an entry point for somebody wanting to check it out and learn more about the community. But it does also mean others with very different contexts can find it and it might be the exact opposite message of what they need to hear right now. That can be mediated a little by making my context as clear as I can, but it will always be true that one message can&#39;t be perfect for everyone in all contexts at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;expository-preaching&quot;&gt;Expository Preaching&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the New Leaf class, they talk about expository as the default approach to preaching in evangelical circles. This approach that is very much focused on walking through the text, helping explain it generally in the order it appears, as opposed to a more topical approach that starts from a current relevant question. It has some big advantages mainly that it keeps the text a little more in its context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I skew a little more expository than most in my church, but still not a lot compared to a lot of evangelicals. I mostly think it&#39;s hard to do really well in a meaningful way in a 15-20 sermon slot, at least not without being part of a longer series or being connected to Adult Education for more help. There just isn&#39;t time to go really deep into Scriptural context. There are exceptions: the first in my recent double header was much more expository, and I will have the final piece of a series on Ephesians that will likely end up a bit more expository. The New Leaf session touches on some of the problem with expository as well, that it often ends up arrogantly projecting what we want into the text, while pretending we&#39;re letting it speak for itself, because we do have a social context which does impact our reading whether we like to admit it or not. There is really no such thing as &amp;quot;letting the text speak for itself&amp;quot;; we&#39;re always interpreting. But if you&#39;re able to still come in with that honesty about your perspective, then yes, I think it is valuable to have some sermons that start from the text and some that start from the topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;is-it-antiquated&quot;&gt;Is It Antiquated?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New Leaf&#39;s class raises the point that a lot of people think of preaching as an antiquated form. Having one person speak and others listen is not a very good way to learn. So why do we still do it? Several years ago, one member of our church preached on why he preached, and he essentially said that while only hearing something is bad for learning it, formulating your thoughts enough to be able to preach it is a very good way to learn or wrestle with something. So preaching is good for the preacher at least, if they&#39;re being honest in their wrestling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is close to what I&#39;m often going for now when I preach: I want to model wrestling with the Scripture text and our tradition and our current world, and invite others into that wrestling. They don&#39;t have to conclude the same on whatever topic as I do. I don&#39;t care about that. But I do care that they are called into the kind of community that is willing to wrestle through the hard parts of life together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s also where I see the difference in preaching and teaching. Teaching is a fairly intellectual lecture or discussion getting deep into a specific issue, and in our church the Adult Education hour does that more. Preaching is more about inviting each other into a community around Jesus. That requires a lot more humility than the approach where the preacher is declaring God&#39;s perfect truth, and it probably takes more of a community where preaching duties are more shared in order to avoid only hearing one voice, but it&#39;s much more powerful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-role-of-the-sermon&quot;&gt;The Role of the Sermon&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the sermon is valuable, but it probably shouldn&#39;t be the absolute only thing that matters. I&#39;m a big proponent on doing the Eucharist/communion regularly, that embodied act of remembering the Jesus story together in an extremely tangible way. I personally do not care as much about music, but I know a lot do. I&#39;m also a big fan of communal prayer, sharing our thanks and requests together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think sermons are often important, especially as an entry point for somebody who is new. It is the most opportunity to clearly convey what the community thinks this whole Jesus thing is about, and we live in a world where a lot of people no longer have any idea what this Jesus thing is about. So I especially want to preserve the sermon on days like Easter or leading up to Christmas, when people are most likely to come for the first time, or the first time in a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That doesn&#39;t necessarily mean it has to be the central feature of every service. It doesn&#39;t even mean that it has to be present in every service. On the opposite end from Easter may be something like Thanksgiving, at least in our church: a lot of people are away, and if they are there they are likely tired juggling family commitments, there is highly unlikely to be anybody new showing up, and while gratitude broadly is certainly coherent with Christianity Thanksgiving is not a specifically Christian holiday. So that day, our church usually doesn&#39;t have a sermon, instead replacing it with a day of singing and poems. It allows for a more meditative space, which is a valuable change of pace.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hope is a Sewer Rat</title>
    <link href="https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/hope-sewer-rat/" />
    <updated>2024-12-07T21:46:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/hope-sewer-rat/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I love this poem I&#39;ve seen go around social media a couple of times, called Hope is a Sewer Rat by Caitlin Seida.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hope is not the thing with feathers
That comes home to roost
When you need it most.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hope is an ugly thing
With teeth and claws and
Patchy fur that’s seen some shit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s what thrives in the discards
And survives in the ugliest parts of our world,
Able to find a way to go on
When nothing else can even find a way in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s the gritty, nasty little carrier of such
diseases as
optimism, persistence,
Perseverance and joy,
Transmissible as it drags its tail across
your path
and
bites you in the ass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hope is not some delicate, beautiful bird,
Emily.
It’s a lowly little sewer rat
That snorts pesticides like they were
Lines of coke and still
Shows up on time to work the next day
Looking no worse for wear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe sometimes hope actually is the delicate bird that arrives just when you need it and reminds you of a better world. I&#39;m not ruling that out. But a lot of the time, yeah, I think it&#39;s the sewer rat, something that gets beat up by the world over and over again and yet, if we choose to, it comes back for more.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>On Political Distractions</title>
    <link href="https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/distractions/" />
    <updated>2024-11-30T21:46:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/distractions/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Like with &lt;a href=&quot;https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/echo-chambers/&quot;&gt;the &amp;quot;echo chamber&amp;quot; discourse&lt;/a&gt;, I think there&#39;s something deeper in the &amp;quot;distractions&amp;quot; discourse on social media than it appears at first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those unaware, this is how it goes: politician (sometimes other public figure) does a new bad thing while being known to do other bad things, and social media erupts with a debate about whether the new bad thing is a distraction from the other bad things.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-does-that-mean&quot;&gt;What Does That Mean?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is rarely explained what they think it means that something is a distraction. It often just gets labelled a distraction as if it is obvious. But my best guesses at how it is usually interpreted:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some definitely think it means a cold calculated tactic, that the politician is intentionally starting another bad thing so that you&#39;ll stop talking about the other bad thing. The theory is that they can get away with the new bad thing more than the old bad thing, so once everyone&#39;s attention goes to the new bad thing, they&#39;ll end up getting away with both. This is probably sometimes true but I don&#39;t think as often as social media tends to believe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe more often true is a softer version, more like: politician knows that they won&#39;t get away with all the bad things, so they throw as many as they can against the wall and hope some of it sticks. Trump has talked (or had ghost written) to this effect: always ask for the absolute maximum, then you may end up appearing to &amp;quot;compromise&amp;quot; and still getting everything you really wanted. I am somewhat optimistic that&#39;s what is happening with his tariff promise, that he&#39;s making absurd demands and then will &amp;quot;compromise&amp;quot; at very close to the status quo except for one thing he can claim as a political win without actually helping anyone. That&#39;s how the last NAFTA renegotiation went, when it came back basically the same as before except he got to call it a new name and declared a huge victory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;burned-out&quot;&gt;Burned Out&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, to get to the main point, what I suspect people are really trying to say when they declare something a distraction is often more like: I&#39;m overwhelmed and I cannot fight all of these battles at once so I need to opt out of this one. And that is a very important discussion to have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The nature of social media is that it is good for blasting out and consuming a lot of news in little bursts at a time. Pair that with the extremely online left, where it is easy to be stuck digging deeper and deeper into one piece of bad news after another, and it is inevitable that eventually you throw up your hands and declare that it is all too much for one person to handle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is too much for one person to handle. It&#39;s true. I cannot fix all the world&#39;s problems on my own. I can&#39;t even fully understand all the world&#39;s problems on my own. But here&#39;s the important thing: I don&#39;t have to do it all on my own. Neither do you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometimes I think about the modern extremely online left&#39;s emphases on ideas like &amp;quot;justice isn&#39;t justice if it isn&#39;t for everyone.&amp;quot; That&#39;s true, but it can have a paralyzing effect where nobody does anything because we&#39;re all too afraid that we didn&#39;t sufficiently account for all of humanity in our 280 character post. It&#39;s an all or nothing attitude when none of us are capable of doing it all. Sometimes we need to move forward the best we can, get some of it right and some wrong, then take feedback, then move forward again with that feedback in mind so that we get a little bit less wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to be better at finding the one or two or three things we are going to really focus on, and maybe stay loosely aware of the rest, particularly in how that might impact your few. But for the rest of the constant barrage of issues we are being reminded of, we often need to take a deep breath and decide to trust that somebody else is going to fight that fight while you&#39;re fighting your fight. You can&#39;t do it all. That&#39;s ok. Maybe the new thing is a distraction for you and the work that you need to prioritize. You might need to say no to some things because you already said yes to a more important (to you) thing. Just be careful about projecting that onto everyone else, lest you end up discouraging those for whom it is their important work.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>On Echo Chambers</title>
    <link href="https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/echo-chambers/" />
    <updated>2024-11-24T21:46:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/echo-chambers/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;A common sentiment is that in the modern world, people are too stuck in their echo chambers. This is mostly used as an insult against the extremely online left wing, most recently a lot about &lt;a href=&quot;https://bsky.app/&quot;&gt;Bluesky&lt;/a&gt;. Interestingly, the extremely online right wing doesn&#39;t get the same accusation as much, even though they&#39;re steeped in much more extreme networks. But that&#39;s an immediate tangent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-bad-faith-version&quot;&gt;The Bad Faith Version&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many of the people talking about this are doing so in bad faith. They seem to mean that for some reason those with more left political leanings are obligated to give all of their time, money, and data to a far-right billionaire and his network that has been actively suppressing them and sending harassment at them for years. Let&#39;s be clear that&#39;s bad. You have a right to block somebody who walks in to your social feeds and starts hurling abuse at you or at anyone else, just as much as you have a right to kick out somebody who tries to walk into living room and commit the same abuses in person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even more to the point, some people absolutely should be blocked because they are often actively trying to drive engagement through anger, which benefits them, including sometimes financially. Don&#39;t try to dunk on them first. Just take away their precious engagement and let them shout into the void. Make it less profitable to be spreading hate and maybe some of them will even learn to stop spreading hate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, am extremist billionaire does not have the right to demand that more people buy ads from him or use his network just because he wants them to. We are under no such obligation to make him even richer. We are under no such obligation to support his false claims that he has turned X into the beacon of free speech.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there have been plenty of responses already on the Internet pointing out things like this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-good-faith-version&quot;&gt;The Good Faith Version&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where this gets more interesting is that I&#39;m not convinced that&#39;s what everybody means when they criticize echo chambers. I believe some do have a more good faith desire behind the complaint, even if they aren&#39;t explaining it in quite the way I am about to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of the complaints say they want to restore respectful dialogue with people we don&#39;t agree with everything about. On its surface, that is a good goal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately that is not what social media is built to be. It is not designed to have that respectful deep dialogue. Messages are short, struggling to find space for nuance. They are mostly one-directional; one of the interesting changes years ago was shifting from social networking to social media. Networking implies some equality and finding your peers. Media implies there are some creators and the rest are consumers. That&#39;s a dynamic that is very hard to have real hard conversation within. Social media may occasionally be able to put a bandaid on loneliness, but it isn&#39;t a replacement for real community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I think the good faith interpretation here is that people are realizing that social media is not a replacement for real community and they want that real community again. Where they make a mistake is thinking the way to get it again is by forcing everyone to be on a particular toxic site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-emerging-church-and-dialogue&quot;&gt;The Emerging Church and Dialogue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&#39;s get this back to the realm of Christianity. I recently listened through &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.homebrewedchristianty.com/2023/10/16/the-story-of-the-emerging-church-movement/&quot;&gt;the Emerged series from Homebrewed Christianity&lt;/a&gt;, looking back on the emerging church movement. This was a big movement for my own life, although I was not tied to any official part of that movement and was largely at the end of it. But something that came up a lot resonated with my experience: it was largely based in friendship. You could have extensive tough conversations with people completely different than you, sometimes coming to very different conclusions, because of a friendship that came from wrestling with the same questions over time. In the earliest days, that was in small meetup groups you would find online, and show up without any idea of who else would be there. You might show up and see an evangelical youth pastor hoping nobody from his church sees him, and a 16 year old Episcopalian contemplating faith for the first time, and a 70 year old Eastern Orthodox priest who wants to learn more about younger generations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Later, closer to my time, a lot of these conversations happened in blogs. We found our 20 or 30 blogs that we loved, loaded them in our Google Reader (which no longer exists but RSS still does), and we would have long and tough conversations with a lot of the same people over months and years in the comments or through writing our own blog posts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those largely faded out as social media took over, which gets us back to the problems I named earlier. There are some places somewhat modelling those ideas of dialogue in longer deeper discussions with those you don&#39;t fully agree with, like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newleafnetwork.ca/&quot;&gt;New Leaf Network&lt;/a&gt; here in Canada, but the large scale movement is no more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-now&quot;&gt;What Now?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what do we do about that? Personally, I think trying to change the nature of social media is swimming upstream. You might occasionally manage to foster some real respectful conversation with somebody you disagree with. But it&#39;s hard because the medium fundamentally opposes it. It&#39;s even harder when there&#39;s a profit motive for the rich people controlling the social media to maximum their profits at the expense of everything else, which largely means optimizing engagement through rage and blocking links out to reliable sources.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We could try to go back to blogs, if we&#39;re going to focus on tech. Hey look, I&#39;m sort of doing that, but without comments - less because I don&#39;t want dialogue and more because I don&#39;t want to pay for and maintain a server. But I suspect it&#39;s still too close to social media for most people to be able to change their default ways of thinking, so many now will still walk into the comments ready to pick a fight, not form a community over the next decade.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So this is where I sound old-fashioned: churches need to be building real community, in person or online small groups. And they need to be inviting others into that real community. That real community takes a lot of time, it takes a lot of patience with each other, it takes a willingness to confess when we&#39;ve hurt each other and lot of forgiveness when we do mess up. It also takes intentional infrastructure: where can they meet in a place that is reachable, which is not a given in North America&#39;s sprawling urban design? What time, when so many people have no time left at the end of a workday to commit to something else? Those don&#39;t have easy answers. But if we aren&#39;t even trying, our social problems are only to get worse.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>AMBS: Challenging Christian Nationalism</title>
    <link href="https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/ambs-challenging-christian-nationalism/" />
    <updated>2024-11-24T21:46:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/ambs-challenging-christian-nationalism/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;See below for a great presentation at Anabaptist Mennonite Biblical Seminary about Christian Nationalism. This was before the US election, but it&#39;s no less relevant now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ubCYHYa0KKM?si=cK3CyuLnMfLa4znX&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; referrerpolicy=&quot;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has a lot of similar themes to my recent pair of sermons which I will hopefully be posting soon, but obviously it is longer and much more academic, getting into more precise details of movements in the US.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>To Remember Is To Work for Peace</title>
    <link href="https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/remembrance-day/" />
    <updated>2024-11-11T21:46:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/remembrance-day/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Remembrance Day often carries two different tones with it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;War is horrible. We honour those who died by grieving that horror with all its lost lives.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;War is super important and we need our national team to win, so support our troops and cheer when they do more violence than the other side does.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anabaptists like myself are mostly ok with the first part. We hold in high esteem those who would sacrifice their lives for others. The only real question is how many soldiers really choose to sacrifice their lives, rather than being pushed to by nationalist forces who stand to gain. If it isn&#39;t chosen then it isn&#39;t really a sacrifice on their part. It is often more accurate to say that some politicians and war profiteers sacrificed those soldiers&#39; lives for their profit. But I digress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s the second part that we start to have a problem with Remembrance Day. Anabaptists remain firm that our loyalty is to Jesus, not to any nation, and Jesus is pretty clear about the whole nonviolent love of enemies thing. So grieving violence makes complete sense. The nationalist jingoism, the cheerleading of violence as long as it is against THEM instead of against US, does not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For several years, Mennonites have often worn a red pin that says &amp;quot;To remember is to work for peace.&amp;quot; That might be in addition to the poppy (if we&#39;re focusing more on the first part above) or instead of (if we&#39;re focusing more on the second part). Either way, this is the most essential part in my worldview: if you truly grieve wars and violence more generally, if you truly want to remember and honour those who died, you will want to work to keep that from happening again whether that&#39;s in Ukraine or Canada or Palestine or anywhere else. Being a peacemaker is not a simple opting out of violence; it must be an active work toward a more just and whole world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s my quick reflection of the day. Here&#39;s Marlene Epp speaking at my church, Rockway Mennonite, about some of the history of Mennonites with Remembrance Day:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/drsv8C1PFk0?si=lhG0xUPctLHa-XUk&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; referrerpolicy=&quot;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Recycling Christianity</title>
    <link href="https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/recycling-christianity/" />
    <updated>2024-10-06T21:46:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/recycling-christianity/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This was the second of a two-part sermon series, following up from &lt;a href=&quot;https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/cult-innocence/&quot;&gt;The Cult of Innocence&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;scripture-texts&quot;&gt;Scripture Texts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bibles.org/bible/1fd99b0d5841e19b-02/search?passageId=MRK.9.38-MRK.9.47&amp;amp;q=matthew%207%3A1-6%2C%2013-20&quot;&gt;Matthew 7:1-6, 13-20&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s the video version from the church&#39;s YouTube:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/Ys1wgVjDxDc?si=cJPmqE1aaPdl2M4Y&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; referrerpolicy=&quot;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;transcript&quot;&gt;Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The transcript is cleaned up a little to be more general and shareable to the wider public. I also always end up improvising a little when I speak, so what is written down is not exactly the same as what would be captions on the video.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;previously-on&quot;&gt;Previously On…&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those who weren’t here last week, this is essentially part two of last week’s sermon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A quick recap of the key points:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Mark text, Jesus teaches against wielding power over and against others, instead celebrating those who centre and liberate the marginalized. It was specifically children in that text, but I feel confident to make it a general statement because of everything else Jesus did and taught. He criticizes the disciples for seeking that kind of dominating power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The cult of innocence is a term from Brian McLaren about the attitude that often supports that quest for power. That’s when we believe that we are superior to others and thus justified – maybe even required – to rule over them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The James text gave some tips on avoiding that trap as a community: confession, singing, and praying. These help us avoid defining ourselves primarily by how we are better than somebody else and in a more positive way instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;defining-christianity&quot;&gt;Defining Christianity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s on that question of definition that I am going to pick up. We are a Christian church. We just read from the Christian Scriptures, about the teachings of the one we call the Christ. Not everybody here would individually call themselves a Christian. No judgement from me. There’s a lot of good reasons why that might be. But “here” is a church in the Christian tradition, so I am speaking communally and assuming that at the very least, you aren’t that uncomfortable by others using the label.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does that mean, to define ourselves as Christian? In &lt;em&gt;Do I Stay Christian&lt;/em&gt;’s introduction, Brian McLaren names several different categories under which “Christian” can be defined. He includes historically or culturally, institutionally, doctrinally, liturgically or programmatically, spiritually or experientially, moralistically, missionally, demographically, politically, socially, and linguistically. That’s a lot of options. There’s a lot of room in there to able to fit in one definitional category while being completely opposite in another category.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s where the conflict really comes in for me: it’s undeniable that when many people in our culture hear the word “Christian,” they picture a violent white patriarchal nationalist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I could get into a long rant about the many things I disagree with the current Christian nationalist movement about. Some of those rants have been in previous drafts of this message. But to sum up the heart of Christian nationalism, I’m going to quote one Donald Trump who said, “there should be no more important voice than the voice of Christians.” As usual for Donald Trump, that was amid some rambling that wasn’t entirely coherent, but that line was clear. It was also clear in the context that he meant white conservative Christians. They believe that they have the right to enforce a hierarchy with them at the top ruling over the rest of us, because our voices don’t matter as much. It’s running headfirst into the cult of innocence quest for power. That’s where I start to have a hard time talking about it as a truly Christian movement. It is in some of the definitional categories that McLaren names, mostly the socio-political ones. But I see no way around that it is blatantly contradictory to the way of Jesus. It is quite literally anti-Christ.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;true-christianity&quot;&gt;“True” Christianity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some of you might be tensing up right now at that kind of language. Most of us can probably think of some time in our life that we’ve heard that real Christians always do x, or don’t believe y. Maybe that was an attack on you personally, maybe it was a more generalized statement. You might have also heard that with more specific labels like Mennonite. Me questioning whether this is truly a Christian movement might hit a sore spot. I understand that impulse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many years ago, there was a huge story that took over Christian social media. World Vision USA decided to allow LGBTQ people on staff. There’s not a lot of practical reasons why they wouldn’t have been allowed in the first place. It’s not like being in World Vision’s IT or letter translation or accounting has some great spiritual authority to “spread their sinful lifestyle” or whatever. But that&#39;s not my main point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In response, thousands of evangelicals suddenly dropped support for sponsor children through World Vision. They even did that in Canada, even though World Vision Canada had never had a policy blocking LGBTQ staff in the first place. For these evangelicals, the life of the child they had spent years supporting and building a relationship with was easy to set aside. It was less important than making a culture war statement to maintain their cult of innocence as superior to LGBTQ people. And they won, at least in the short term, as World Vision USA brought back the policy after about a week of watching all their work collapse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I posted on Facebook how I thought this showed some very skewed priorities. By this point, I was publicly calling myself an Anabaptist. For those who don’t know, that’s the broader branch of Christianity that Mennonites are a part of.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In response to my post, I got a message from a former pastor. He had also moved to an Anabaptist community. He let me know that I really shouldn’t be calling myself an Anabaptist if I supported any kind of LGBTQ equality. That wasn’t even the point of the post I had made, but it was also true that I did support that, so probably not worth fighting over that distinction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how should I respond to that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-options&quot;&gt;The Options&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In thinking back on that experience, I found the options that he was giving me – one he said explicitly and others I thought were there implicitly - mapped well with what McLaren named for something on the surface to be completely different. He discusses the options that were presented by the Christian colonialism project.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found this even more interesting because those options also largely map to the same options that Christian nationalists try to force on the rest of us today. There is a commonality in how this dominating power mindset works. These are the options:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can try to become one of them and share in the power. Maybe that’s at the cost of your integrity. There have been stories of far right talking heads who don’t really believe a lot of it, but they realized it was very profitable. Maybe in some cases it’s at the cost of other aspects of your identity, especially if that&#39;s a more marginalized identity. But you can try to play their power game. What that pastor probably wanted most was for me to renounce my heresy and return to &amp;quot;true Christianity,&amp;quot; willing to sacrifice LGBTQ people for my own gain.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can stick around but shut up and give them everything they want. Basically, be the subservient class that they need to exploit in order for any of their plans to actually work. For somebody to be at the top, there have to be people underneath them. Maybe I could keep using the Anabaptist label but shut up about equality. Stop rocking the boat.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can leave, at least in theory. You sometimes hear that rhetoric from the nationalists: if you don’t like the way I want my country to be, you should just leave. It’s never as easy to migrate as they seem to think it is. It’s not that easy to get into what they consider their country and not as easy to get out of their country into other countries. But maybe from that conversation I should have concluded it is best to forsake the Anabaptist label. That is what my former pastor explicitly recommended. I think he knew me enough to know I wasn’t going to do the first two, even if they did feel implied.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Or the final option, when all else fails, especially if you tried to put up a fight, you can die. One of the leaders of Project 2025, writing policy for a Trump presidency, promised a revolution but that “it would be bloodless if the left wants it to be.” Essentially, he was saying he’d like everyone else to take option 2, but he’s willing to do option 4. Fortunately, this one did not feel like it was relevant in that short discussion with my former pastor.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;discerning-and-judging&quot;&gt;Discerning and Judging&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think the Matthew text helps point us toward having more than those four options. But it’s true that it might look self-contradictory at first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jesus says to not judge others. We are supposed to focus on our own weaknesses first and then we can gently help others with theirs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But then we also hear to not throw pearls to pigs. That requires that you can tell what the pearls are, and who the pigs are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also get that there is a narrow path of life and a wide path of destruction. The way of Jesus surrendering power out of love for others is hard, but it brings life. It’s a lot easier to seek power over others. That is the default way our world operates, hence calling it the wide path, even though it leads to a lot of destruction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And finally, it says that we should identify false prophets by their fruit. We should ask questions like: what are the consequences of people who say they represent God or absolute truth? Do their attitudes and actions result in better loving their neighbours, particularly the most marginalized, or does it spread fear and a desire to dominate others?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So… how are we supposed to identify the “pigs” and the false prophets and those on the wide path, if we aren’t supposed to judge?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I believe there are two different types of judgement involved here. The judgement in the first section is about superiority, placing ourselves above others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, to that, Jesus says we need to make sure we’re aware of our own weaknesses. That was last week’s message. This is an ongoing project, not a one-time thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then once we have some clarity, we can move into the different type of judging, which we could also call discernment. Discernment is one of those Christianese terms. We have a gifts discernment committee, which basically means volunteer recruitment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I decided to see how much consensus there was on the meaning of the word discernment, so I entered it into a Bing search. Yes, I use Bing. I will not be defending myself on that. But it gave me two definitions at the top of the results:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The ability to judge well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(in Christian contexts) perception in the absence of judgement with a view to obtaining spiritual guidance and understanding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I thought, wow, good job Bing. That second one really nailed what I was trying to say. Discernment in this sense requires the absence of judgement. If you are too caught up in a superiority complex, you can’t perceive the spiritual guidance you’re looking for. So not only do we have two different ideas of judgement here, they’re fundamentally contradictory to each other.
That discernment includes when societal forces are pushing in the complete opposite direction of what we see as the values of Jesus. That’s particularly true in the big central things Jesus talked about a lot, like our relationship with power over and against the marginalized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s always going to be tempting to take that discernment right back into judgement. The people participating in those societal forces may be our “enemies” in that they have contrary goals. We can be honest about that. But that doesn’t mean we hate the people or that we spread fear about them. Back to the James text from last week, we restore people where we can. We get them out of their participation in the systems of oppression. We do not restore or defend the systems of oppression.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think this distinction helps set up another option for us.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;recycling-christianity&quot;&gt;Recycling Christianity&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is where I come back to that conversation with the former pastor. I did abandon the label of evangelical about that time, so why not also Anabaptist or Christian?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The big difference was that by that point, I knew a lot of Anabaptists and other Christians who clearly did not have a problem with me. Many were explicitly and publicly affirming of LGBTQ equality in the church as well as legally. Even the ones who were not fully affirming still universally agreed with me that it is bad to abandon a sponsor child just because World Vision might employ a gay person. The former pastor was the anomaly in my life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s the most important part to me. It’s essentially a different angle to how last week’s message ended: we do often have to name the bad thing, but we can’t stop there. We have to be prepared to do the hard part of offering something better. Loudly. Publicly. Without any shame attached.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;McLaren talks about recycling Christianity. He acknowledges that there are some harmful things that need to be thrown out; maybe there’s nothing left to be redeemed about them. But he also cautions that ideas or labels don’t simply go away. If we stop using certain language because others are using it in a harmful way, all that leaves us with is their harmful definition. So instead of abandoning Christian identity, we could seek to recycle or re-consecrate, make it holy again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This also applies to more specific ideas in how we understand the world. The whole concept of how Christians relate to LGBTQ people had been recycled for me in time. I knew that there were options other than trying to deny them every legal right and every community participation. It made it so much easier to say “no” to that pastor because I had already said “yes” to something better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m going to end with a bit of a rapid fire of some of those big ideas that maybe need to be recycled. These need to be taken back from what a lot of people think is “the Christian meaning.” I don’t think it is a coincidence that a lot of these conflicts in definition go back to questions of power and the cult of innocence. Many things within the biblical and early Christian context were radically upending power structures, standing up to Roman authority. But they have since been redefined away, into justifications for why some should dominate everyone else. That’s to the point that most people – including a lot of people in churches - don’t even realize how they once meant the opposite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Justice and peace: we often hear justice talked about as punishing those we think have broken the rules. It’s justice to put somebody in jail when they’ve done something wrong. Peace is often treated as not currently having large-scale violence, mainly because you’ve enacted justice on the bad guys. That’s a very Roman Empire and European perspective. What if instead, it meant something closer to the Hebraic worldview, where justice is about making the world whole and equitable for everyone?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tied into that is salvation: this is often used to mean fire insurance to avoid Hell when we die. What if instead it means what it meant in the Exodus story, and many other places in the Bible? There it’s an oppressed people escaping their oppressors, and sometimes its the oppressors escaping being involved in the systems of oppression. The Bible talks a lot about judgement but has little concern with an afterlife.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apocalypse: that’s always a fun one. We often hear that spoken of as the end of the world. And usually that’s pictured as God will violently destroy the bad guys and put the good guys in charge – that’s us. Maybe that’s through a war in the Middle East, which is even more timely this week than usual. Self-fulfilling prophecy is a thing. But what if apocalypse meant what it originally meant, an unveiling? There’s a reason why the last book of English Bibles is called Revelation. It’s a poetic look behind the curtain at the forces of domination in the world and how God overcomes them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gospel: it’s supposed to mean good news but often it is phrased as very bad news. We are evil sinners who will burn in Hell if we don’t submit to the right religion. Isn’t that great news? What if it was the Gospel of Jesus instead, that God’s Kingdom of love and justice is among us right now? What if it’s the Gospel of texts like Mary’s Magnificat, that God overcomes evil including removing tyrants from their throne? Now that sounds like some good news.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have no interest in the violent white patriarchal nationalist Christianity that openly mocks the words of Jesus as “too woke.” But that recycled liberatory Christianity, the one that takes Jesus’ challenges to power seriously? That’s a Christianity I can get behind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;books&quot;&gt;Books&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do I Stay Christian: A Guide for the Doubters, the Disappointed, and the Disillusioned&lt;/em&gt; by Brian McLaren. This is a very pastoral book taking an honest look at the concept of a Christian identity. It acknowledges a lot of very serious harms both past and present that would justifiably cause us to abandon the label. It also includes practical reasons why you may choose to keep the label despite those things, and then offers some suggestions on how to proceed either way. In part one, I borrowed the concept of the cult of innocence. In this part I borrowed some more ideas: the colonial options and recycling Christian language.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How To Have an Enemy: Righteous Anger and the Work of Peace&lt;/em&gt; by Melissa Florer-Bixler, a Mennonite USA pastor. This is a great examination of how Jesus responded to very real enemies and taught us to do the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;God and Empire&lt;/em&gt; by John Dominic Crossan. This is a good overview of the Bible’s conflict between an imperial worldview and a bottom-up peace worldview. At risk of disagreeing with one of the greatest living New Testament scholars, I do think he puts Revelation in the wrong category, though, missing out on what other scholars will point out are the nonviolent themes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jesus and John Wayne: How White Evangelicals Corrupted a Faith and Fractured a Nation&lt;/em&gt; by Kristen K Du Mez. This covers decades of the history of white evangelicalism in the United States and how it got to be where it is today, especially in terms of the priority on a macho violent masculinity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Kingdom, the Power, and the Glory: American Evangelicals in an Age of Extremism&lt;/em&gt;. This is written by a journalist who is himself a white evangelical, son of a white evangelical pastor, about the descent of US white evangelicalism particularly since 2016. He is focused less on the major influencers and more on the impact on church congregations, where it is now not unusual for people to simultaneously declare they are the only real Christians and anything Jesus said must be dismissed because it is “woke.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Disunity in Christ: Uncovering the Hidden Forces that Keep Us Apart&lt;/em&gt; by Christena Cleveland. This is a look at divisions within the Christian Church through the lens of social psychology. I read this book many years ago, before the current wave of Christian nationalism really took off, and it would be interesting to revisit now or to ask Christena what she would say differently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;youtube-and-podcasts&quot;&gt;YouTube and Podcasts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reclaimingmytheology.org/&quot;&gt;Reclaiming My Theology&lt;/a&gt; is a podcast hosted by Brandi Miller that is “taking our theology back from ideas and systems that oppress.” Season 1 focused on white supremacy, season 2 on patriarchy and purity culture, and she has now started a new season on empire. The current season is the most directly related, but the others do tie in as well. It is perhaps my most recommended Christian podcast.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IkES4X_qb6c&quot;&gt;For Our Daughters&lt;/a&gt; is a short documentary from Kristen K Du Mez, author of Jesus and John Wayne (listed above under Books). It is focused on how authoritarian theologies lead to abuse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.homebrewedchristianty.com/category/podcast/&quot;&gt;Homebrewed Christianity&lt;/a&gt; has had a lot of episodes relevant here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5J1q8iLvD08&quot;&gt;Do I Stay Christian? a conversation with Brian McLaren about his new book (youtube.com)&lt;/a&gt; This is the intro to a series with Brian about the book cited above.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Several conversations on a regular basis with Diana Butler Bass which often touch on intersections of religion and politics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://trippfuller.com/2023/06/20/adam-clark-from-contemplation-to-liberation/&quot;&gt;Adam Clark: From Contemplation to Liberation&lt;/a&gt;. From the episode description, it includes “the struggles of those trying to stay Christian when the church testifies against it.”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bQcL0t73O5Y&quot;&gt;Project 2025: A Hellish Legal Vision for America, by Legal Eagle&lt;/a&gt;. This is a pretty good summary of major points of Project 2025, the policy manifesto of the US right. Also available ad-free with a &lt;a href=&quot;https://nebula.tv/featured&quot;&gt;Nebula&lt;/a&gt; subscription. It isn’t a Christian refutation of it, but a US legal one.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;other-possible-texts&quot;&gt;Other Possible Texts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike the first week, this week wasn’t based on the lectionary, and the idea really came from extending last week’s text, so I needed to select at least one more Scripture text that tied in for this week. I ultimately selected the Matthew text, but these are others I considered.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bibles.org/bible/1fd99b0d5841e19b-02/1JN.4?passageId=1JN.4.1-1JN.4.10&amp;amp;q=1%20john%204&quot;&gt;1 John 4&lt;/a&gt;: this shares some similarities with the Matthew text from the Sermon on the Mount. It similarly names that there are false prophets. Matthew says they are known by their fruit; this says they are known by denying that Jesus is from God. I think this is saying a similar thing. If you believe Jesus is from God, you believe he has some authority in his wisdom teaching about surrendering power out of love for others. I didn’t feel like I could get to the point as quickly as with the Matthew text.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were a couple more in the same category of identifying false teachers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bibles.org/bible/1fd99b0d5841e19b-02/2PE.2?passageId=2PE.2.1-2PE.2.10&amp;amp;q=2%20peter%202&quot;&gt;2 Peter 2&lt;/a&gt;: this one is the most angry about false teachers but didn’t have as clear of a dichotomy for the alternative, which I wanted.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bibles.org/bible/1fd99b0d5841e19b-02/2TI.4?passageId=2TI.4.1-2TI.4.5&amp;amp;q=2%20Timothy%204%3A1-5&quot;&gt;2 Timothy 4:1-5&lt;/a&gt;: a shorter segment acknowledging how false teachers will lure people in with attractive myths – like the superiority of your group over others – but is mostly focused on doing the hard work of building an alternative.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bibles.org/bible/1fd99b0d5841e19b-02/ACT.5?passageId=ACT.5.33-ACT.5.42&amp;amp;q=Acts%205%3A33-42&quot;&gt;Acts 5:33-42&lt;/a&gt;: the argument of Gamaliel here is interesting, and at least partly coherent with how I am approaching Christian nationalism. Distance ourselves from them. Make it clear that there is a distinction. But it’s not actively seeking to kill them, instead trusting that if it is not truly from God it will not work out well for them in the end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bibles.org/bible/1fd99b0d5841e19b-02/EPH.6?passageId=EPH.6.10-EPH.6.17&amp;amp;q=Ephesians%206%3A10-17&quot;&gt;Ephesians 6:10-17&lt;/a&gt;. This is a lot of spiritual warfare language which often makes those of us in the peace tradition uncomfortable, but the key part to me is verse 12, that “we aren’t fighting against human enemies but against rulers, authorities, forces of cosmic darkness, and spiritual powers of evil in the heavens” (CEB). I think this is helpful to remember that while we cannot divide the world between us good guys and those bad guys, we also can’t deny that evil systems exist, and the way of Jesus stands in opposition to them. I am tempted to do a “recycling” sermon on the concept of spiritual warfare at some point. Update: I am now doing a sermon on this text in an upcoming Ephesians series.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://bibles.org/bible/1fd99b0d5841e19b-02/ACT.8?passageId=ACT.8.9-ACT.8.18&amp;amp;q=Acts%208%3A9-23&quot;&gt;Acts 8:9-23&lt;/a&gt;: see the deleted scene “Simon the Great” below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;deleted-scenes&quot;&gt;Deleted Scenes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are some pieces that got cut for time, but are a direction I went down at some point during the process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;more-examples-of-christian-nationalism&quot;&gt;More Examples of Christian Nationalism&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[I ultimately cut this down because I think the core of Christian nationalism was clear enough that I didn’t need multiple quotes about it, which would have taken time away from what we do about it. Some of this did get included in a shorter form.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might have heard news recently of Project 2025, the policy document associated with but not directly a part of the Trump campaign. It started gaining a lot of attention after one of its leaders made a comment that sounded very similar to the options for subjects of colonial Christianity. He promised that they would bring about a new American Revolution, but it would be bloodless “if the Left wants it to be.” He wants the Left to take option 2, to shut up and not fight back, but he’s willing to go to option 4.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently, a post came across my social media feed from a man who wrote a book in defence of Christian nationalism. His tweet, or whatever they’re called now, says, “Christianity – as the true religion affirming what is true, good and beautiful – commands you to love all but to prefer your people over other people.” If you don’t know anything about Christianity except what the nationalists say, you might think, oh, ok. But if you’ve heard anything from the Sermon on the Mount, or the Good Samaritan, or any of Paul’s many writings about breaking down divisions in the church, or lots of other biblical texts as well as historical teaching, you’re just left saying “what are you talking about?” It’s not even logically possible when you think about it. What exactly does love even mean if you are saying to somebody that you “love” that in all practical ways you prefer them less?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another recent quote that stood out to me was from Donald Trump himself. In a call with the National Faith Advisory Board, he said:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every day, she’s [Kamala Harris] flooding our country with millions and millions of criminal illegal aliens. And wants, to make them citizens, she wants to have them vote, which will destroy the voting powers of Christian conservatives forever. And once that starts happening, and once you get those numbers involved, you lose everything that you’ve had. You’ve had more than you had now, but we’re going to get it higher than ever before. There’s no more, and there should be no more important voice than the voice of Christians.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of that is his trademark incoherence and I don’t really know what he meant. There’s also obviously a lot that is just factually incorrect. But he did get across a couple of his key points.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conservative Christians should be operating out of fear that they are going to lose what power they had. And I think one of the incoherent bits is supposed to be him walking the line that they should be afraid of losing what they have while also feeding the martyr complex which says they already have no power. That’s part of a particular cult of innocence, that they simultaneously believe they should have all the power while denying any power they already have.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conservative Christians should have the most important voice. And that means white conservative Christians. A lot of the immigrants to the US that he is so scared of are conservative Christians, just not white ones.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our political rhetoric in Canada does not usually get as direct as these three quotes, which is why I’m leaned heavily on US examples. We have a lot of the same mindset, but usually our politicians won’t go as far as to directly say that conservative white Christians should have more power over and against everyone else. At most we usually get some vague references to Christian heritage, while letting the more extreme churches or other groups go ahead with the direct language. But as is often true, we are not that far behind the US on this. Even five years ago American politicians also didn’t explicitly declare themselves Christian nationalists the way they do now, so all signs are still suggesting that there are significant forces pushing us in that direction as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;simon-the-great&quot;&gt;Simon the Great&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using &lt;a href=&quot;https://bibles.org/bible/1fd99b0d5841e19b-02/ACT.8?passageId=ACT.8.9-ACT.8.18&amp;amp;q=Acts%208%3A9-23&quot;&gt;Acts 8:9-23&lt;/a&gt; as a second Scripture reading:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It was hard to come up with a Scripture text for the category of those using the Jesus name for selfish power-seeking reasons. There’s a practical reason for that. The Scriptural canon only includes text up to about the end of the first century, which was a couple of centuries before Christians had much cultural or political power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I did think of the story of Simon the Great in Acts 8. He is first established as being a powerful magician, earning the name the Great. He comes to believe in and preach the message of Jesus. But like the disciples in the Mark text last week, it seems like he hasn’t quite understood some of Jesus’ counter-cultural messages about power. When he sees Peter and John doing miraculous things, he wants to buy the Holy Spirit’s power. Peter’s response is harsh. He rebukes him for his belief that God’s gifts can be bought with money. God is not concerned with helping the powerful become even more powerful, and Peter calls out Simon’s “wicked intent” to make the Holy Spirit a tool for his power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simon is a bit like the modern Christian nationalists. He has the language of Christianity, maybe even sincerely believes a lot of it, but primarily because he thinks he can use it to amass more power. He’s still missing a huge part of the Jesus message that upends his whole concept of power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;rockway-constitution&quot;&gt;Rockway Constitution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[This was meant to help remind more of the themes from the previous week, that we are not immune to nationalist and cult of innocent attitudes.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And, as I talked about last week, we are also wrong if we have that cult of innocence attitude, even if it is to accomplish completely different policy goals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thomas (our pastor) knew roughly what I was going to speak about these two weeks, and he sent me the 1982 constitution of Rockway because he saw a line in there that stood out to him. Under the heading of Evangelism / Social Concerns, it says the church “shall actively endeavour to bring spiritual healing and nourishment both to those within and outside its numbers” – ok - and that we “shall work toward the achievement of Christian standards of social conditions locally, nationally, and internationally.” This church, at its founding, clearly believed that “Christian standards” was something worth sharing, that there was some way that Christianity was meant to be an influence in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What that section doesn’t answer is the important part to me: how? How do we go about spreading Christian “standards”? “Standards” is the specific wording that jumped out to me and probably to a lot of you. Something like wisdom teaching or even ethical principles I would be able to swallow a bit more. Standards maybe conveys a bit more uniformity and a bit more legalism, that these are the rules we all have to follow, and in this context, that might imply that we want to force others to follow. But that’s reading a lot into one word written 40 years ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There is a little bit promising in another section, emphasizing that the church is a voluntary community. If you put the two together, that means that the spreading of those Christian standards can’t be done by force or coercion, and that is traditionally the Mennonite position at least on paper. But I didn’t see anywhere that described how it would be done instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;pearls-and-pigs&quot;&gt;Pearls and Pigs&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[In my quick breakdown of the Matthew text, I briefly had a longer tangent on the pearls before swine part.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“They will stomp on the pearls, then turn around and attack you” is an interesting aspect. Sometimes when you try to give a good thing to somebody, they don’t appreciate it. They might even get angry and take it out on you. I wonder if it is stretching the metaphor too much to ponder if the pearls thrown to the pigs are things like the terminology of “Christian”? When I hear Christian nationalists demanding that they are the real Christians, then also shutting down and threatening anybody who dares to point out how Jesus and the Bible seem to disagree with them a lot, that seems to line up to me with what Jesus says here. It sounds a lot like them stomping on the pearls of Jesus’ wisdom teaching, turning around, and attacking you for daring to invite them into it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;staying-defiantly&quot;&gt;Staying Defiantly&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[This was the hardest part to cut, as I wanted to lean in more on the importance of offering an alternative loudly. But ultimately I needed to cut some time and I did get to some of this more quickly.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One phrase that McLaren used for this is “staying defiantly.” That phrase stuck with me: staying defiantly.
When we are wrestling with what to do with Christian identity, we often act like there are two choices:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We can leave defiantly, declaring that we just can’t be a part of this anymore. McLaren doesn’t blame you if you take this option, especially if you are one who is being attacked and marginalized.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We can stay compliantly, shutting up about any problems we see.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Those line up with a couple of the colonialism options from earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;McLaren quotes from Kristin K Du Mez – whose book &lt;em&gt;Jesus and John Wayne&lt;/em&gt; I also recommend - that whether you stay or leave Christianity, you should do so loudly, especially if you have some privilege to lend:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Silence in leaving or remaining will only allow those patterns to persist. It is long past time for white Christians to call out injustice, bigotry, violent rhetoric, disparaging language, racism, misogyny, abuse of power, and the idolatry of Christian nationalism in their own communities, even if doing so comes at a cost. The cost of not doing so is undeniable, and it is a cost largely born by others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are not talking about being the quiet in the land here. We’re talking about being loud, being defiant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;us-politics-parallels&quot;&gt;US Politics Parallels&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Something strange happened after I started formulating this pair of sermons: I started seeing a lot of my key points paralleled in US politics. After thinking a lot about how we need to be able to stay defiantly, keeping a Christian identity while challenging those abusing that label, Joe Biden announced he wouldn’t run again, and Kamala Harris took over as the Democratic candidate. Soon after, a particular strategy started among Democrats: calling the extreme right, who control most of the Republican party now, weird.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of those politicians have spent a long time defining themselves as the real Americans (or the real Canadians) – which is mostly just code for white. At the same time, they have been embracing more and more extreme positions that are actually very unpopular. It’s weird to want to imprison women for medical care, it’s weird to want to ban birth control, it’s weird to want the President to be able to break any laws he wants as long as the Supreme Court is part of the same powerful inner circle, it’s weird to think that the election was stolen simply because your side lost, it’s weird to promise to be a dictator on day one, it’s weird to pledge to fire any civil servant who is not sufficiently loyal to their dear leader, it’s weird to spread lies about immigrants eating pets… Wait, sorry, I said earlier that I wasn’t going to have time for all those details, so I’ll just say, yeah, that’s weird.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And Democrats have done similar with trying to reclaim some other words like freedom, which has been largely defined by the right wing for years as the freedom for those with power to do whatever they want to those without power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think staying defiantly is also very similar to Jesus’ wisdom teachings around turning the other cheek. Without going into the details of that, Jesus was not saying to roll over and give people what they want. It was a way to draw attention to an injustice without perpetuating a cycle of violence. This feels a lot like that, simply declaring in a plain easy to understand way that yeah, some of this is really weird and really unpopular and doing a lot of harm and we don’t have to keep pretending otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Update as I post this online, after the election: this strategy mostly went away. I&#39;m not going to speculate too much on whether that would have made a difference in the result. My point still stands that as Christians, we need to do that defiant reclaiming of definitions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;world-communion-sunday&quot;&gt;World Communion Sunday&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This week is normally World Communion Sunday. It’s a day when most Christian churches around the world all participate in the communion ritual and there is often some emphasis on how despite all our differences, we are all a part of this Jesus tradition.
For some practical reasons we are celebrating it but in a couple of weeks, not actually lining up with everybody else. I preached on that last year. Part of what I said is that while there are lots of food traditions in other religions and cultures, our Communion celebration is a celebration of the particularity of the Jesus tradition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That includes many that call themselves Christian nationalists or other behaviours that we would consider antithetical to the way of Jesus. That introduces some tension with what I’ve said today. How do we celebrate and remember our unity with these other movements, when we are also trying to detach ourselves from them, to paint an alternative? I don’t think that’s a tension we can simply ignore. If we lean entirely into the unity, we are staying quietly, failing to challenge the injustices that we absolutely must challenge. If we rush to cut them off, we risk minimizing the harms being done as well as digging ourselves deeper into a cult of innocence. So, we need to be able to maintain that yes, this Christian tradition that we are a part of has a lot of baggage both past and present, while doing what we can to embody other ways of being within that tradition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;recycling-actions-and-terms&quot;&gt;Recycling Actions and Terms&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[I initially had some more examples of some simple practical actions that embodied some “recycling” as well as some more ideas that might need recycling.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A very simple example: back in the spring we did the blessing of the bicycles. I took a couple of pictures of our overloaded bike stands and of Thomas doing the blessing. I shared some on my social media. I got some likes as expected from some progressive Christians. I also got a couple of replies along the lines of “I have no interest in religion but this is pretty cool.” It was a little drop in the bucket, but it was a counterpoint to what people often think “Christian” means.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or another transit-related one from another local church. When I’m not biking home, I’m usually taking the bus, catching it right beside a United Church. There’s no bench or shelter at that stop. At some point this summer, a pair of lawn chairs appeared, chained to the tree, so those of us waiting for a bus could sit down. It’s also common to see unhoused people sheltering under the overhang there, and I have sheltered there myself when it is raining or really hot. I don’t believe they offer that because they wanted their church to look good. I believe they saw an opportunity to use their property to publicly love their neighbours. But like our bicycle blessing, it made me happy to be reminded that churches like that exist. And that only happens when those loving actions are happening in public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A common one is putting up a rainbow flag on a church. This has happened enough, at least in cities in Ontario, that I think it has achieved some of the “recycling” I talked about. I think those churches are often still thought of as “not real Christianity,” but it is still a step in the right direction that a lot of people now know that there are a lot of churches who are fully affirming of LGBTQ people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Resurrection: that might be used to sound like our bodies don’t matter, because once we die, we’ll ascend into Heaven. But that’s not what resurrection means! It’s not the same thing as ascension. A resurrection requires the redemption of physical bodies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ruling over the Earth, or dominion over the Earth: we might hear language like that to imply that we should pillage and destroy everything for short-term profit, because God put us in charge! It all exists for our pleasure! What if it meant that we should rule like Jesus did, willing to even sacrifice of ourselves for the good of others and the planet?&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Cult of Innocence</title>
    <link href="https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/cult-innocence/" />
    <updated>2024-09-29T21:46:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/cult-innocence/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This was the first of what turned into a two-part sermon recently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;scripture-texts&quot;&gt;Scripture Texts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the lectionary for that day: &lt;a href=&quot;https://bibles.org/bible/1fd99b0d5841e19b-02/JAS.5?passageId=JAS.5.13-JAS.5.20&amp;amp;q=james%205%3A13-20&quot;&gt;James 5:13-20&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://bibles.org/bible/1fd99b0d5841e19b-02/MRK.9?passageId=MRK.9.38-MRK.9.47&amp;amp;q=mark%209%3A38-50&quot;&gt;Mark 9:38-50&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s the video version from the church&#39;s YouTube:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/LQmA_RiR1xk?si=dEqQSImZTuK2nV3V&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; referrerpolicy=&quot;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;transcript&quot;&gt;Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The transcript is cleaned up a little to be more general and shareable to the wider public. I also always end up improvising a little when I speak, so what is written down is not exactly the same as what would be captions on the video.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There’s a lot of weirdness in this text.” That was the opening line of a podcast episode from Yale Divinity where they look at a passage from the lectionary briefly each week, including this week’s Mark text. Yeah, I think that’s a pretty good assessment. Most of it is very familiar if you’ve been around the church for long. But that doesn’t make it that much less weird. There is a lot that feels like non-sequiturs, jumping between loosely related ideas, and in my experience most sermons using it end up picking a specific part to zone in on rather than trying to treat it as one whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first read it in preparation for today, the first section is what I zoned in on. I started with the punchline “whoever is not against us is with us.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was also &lt;a href=&quot;https://bibles.org/bible/1fd99b0d5841e19b-02/NUM.11?passageId=NUM.11.4-NUM.11.13&amp;amp;q=numbers%2011%3A4-29&quot;&gt;a Numbers text in the lectionary for today, chapter 11:4-29&lt;/a&gt;, which has a parallel story. As the disciples do with Jesus in Mark, Moses’ assistant Joshua comes to Moses and tells Moses to stop a couple people from prophesying. Like Jesus in the Mark story, Moses doesn’t see it as a problem at all, instead glad that others are also doing good work, and warns Joshua not to be jealous for his sake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a good lesson there about celebrating those who are acting in line with our values, even if they aren’t active in our church or any church.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was it. That was the whole original sermon idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But unfortunately for those of you think sermons are too long, I kept thinking about these texts. And I kept thinking about the general state of Christianity in North America. And I kept coming across books and podcasts that seemed to have relevant things to say. In fact, I kept thinking about them enough that, in combination with some needed juggling of the worship schedule, this changed from one sermon into two. I will also be speaking again next week, continuing where I leave off today but from a slightly different direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;power-and-christian-institution&quot;&gt;Power and Christian Institution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I looked at more context of the Mark passage to try to connect some of those seemingly disconnected pieces. Sometimes it&#39;s easy when we mostly encounter the Bible in these little segments to forget that these stories were pieced together the way they were for a reason. The Bible didn’t originally have the section headers we have now; those are put in by modern translators and don’t even always agree with each other. It didn’t even have chapter and verse numbers for a long time, or for that matter, even punctuation in the original Greek. Mark was just one long book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found that the section before the lectionary text is helpful for some framing. There, Jesus says that he will be killed and then rise again. The disciples don’t get it. So of course, they don’t ask any follow-up questions, which is a great way to continue to not get it. Then the disciples were debating with each other about who is the greatest. Jesus tells them that whoever wants to be first must be least of all, then calls in a nearby child to emphasize the point: whoever welcomes one of these children in his name welcomes him. That is some of our thematic context: the disciples are trying to position themselves to be near the top of the Jesus follower hierarchy. Jesus tries to teach them to reverse their thinking to prioritize the marginalized, particularly in this case, children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, I think a lot of that conflict is carrying forward into today’s text. We see that the disciples were not upset with what this other person was doing, the casting out demons part. They weren’t even upset with his attitude doing it. They say that he was doing it in Jesus’ name. That phrase is easy for us to read as if the name Jesus or Christ or Christian is a magic word. That is often how it gets used today. Sometimes if we’re being honest, when we end a prayer with “in Jesus’ name”, we’re probably thinking of it like a magic word, thinking that makes it more likely that we’ll get what we want. But also more to the point here, it is often used as a magic word by others like politicians and online social influencers. In that context, it is used to manufacture consent by meaning things like “we’re the good guys, you should vote for us, and you definitely shouldn’t be upset about all the terrible things we are doing because we are CHRISTIANS and that is all that matters!” I’m going to be talking about them more directly next week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in that cultural context, the phrasing “in the name of” means more like “a representative of.” If you do something in the name of the king, you’re saying that you’re doing what the king wanted you to do. A modern twist on that might be “don’t shoot the messenger.” If the messenger is relaying what somebody with higher authority told them to do, and you don’t like the message, the person you’re really upset with is the higher authority, not the messenger. So when the disciples are saying that this exorcist is doing it in Jesus’ name, they probably mean that he was doing it in a way consistent with Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The disciples acknowledged that this exorcist was doing a good thing for the right reasons, but were upset “because he wasn’t following us.” He’s outside of their perceived in-group, outside their desired power structure. And like the previous passage, Jesus again conveys that they’ve missed the point and need to flip their concept of power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re talking about two groups. There are people in the Jesus institution – for lack of a better word - doing good work, and people who are inspired by Jesus but not part of the institution also doing good work. Obviously, there are a lot of other groups in the world, some of which I’ll talk about more in part two next week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the modern world, that latter group is often those who decided they couldn’t put up with all the problems of the church but are still compelled by Jesus in some way. This is a substantial group, mainly because the church has messed up a lot. There’s a lot of reasons why people might have problems with Christianity. Even within the themes of hierarchy and power, there is a lot to work with, past and present. Crusades and witch hunts and inquisitions and colonialism and residential school and many aspects of the current wave of Christian nationalism, and on and on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This quest for power, in both the disciples and the modern church, is usually backed up by what Brian McLaren calls a cult of innocence, in his book &lt;em&gt;Do I Stay Christian&lt;/em&gt;. To justify that your group should rule over others, you need to believe that your group is the correct pure group, and those others are evil that must be punished, or at least inferior that must be controlled.
And it is really easy for me to hear that and think “yeah, I’m so glad I don’t have that attitude like some other people. I’m so glad that I am one of the good guys. I’m never judgemental like those bad guys! We have to find a way to stop them!” And then I realize that I just did my own cult of innocence thinking. It’s a human temptation, not unique to some other group of people we don’t like. It’s one that we aren’t immune to, and the more we think we’re immune to it the more likely we are to fall into it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;cutting-it-off&quot;&gt;Cutting It Off&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That brings us back to the second part of the Mark text. In my experience, a lot of the time I have heard this passage quoted started at verse 43: if your hand causes you to sin, cut it off, and so on. I think I heard that a lot as a teenager and young adult being on the fringes of the purity culture movement. I wasn’t getting nearly the worst of it as my church was pretty good, but I got some tangentially especially as the Internet became a thing. It was used to sell things like monitoring software on your computer to make sure you weren’t accessing pornography. The text was interpreted that you should cut off the ways that you individually sin – and of course the only real sins worth talking about are the sexual ones. And I don’t want to completely squash the general idea there. There is some wisdom in identifying your weak points and having the self-control to avoid them. But also, the extreme focus on sex was bad, and even the better more general version is maybe missing some context here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The context for Mark here is somebody who has harmed a child, or in an interesting bit of phrasing, has caused a child to sin. In that case, the thing that we’re talking about needing to be cut off might be more about harmful power structures and the attitudes that support them within our community, not about individual computer access. They need to be cut off before they become engrained in children, causing them to then continue the cycles of violence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, this is where the cult of innocence attitude jumps in again. See, this text tells me to cut off those terrible Christian nationalists! They are obviously harming the marginalized and amplifying these cycles of violence. I should spend all my free time on the Internet making sure to tell strangers about how those aren’t real Christians, not like I am!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then I check myself again. For one, arguing with strangers on the Internet is mostly counterproductive. But I think more importantly, it leads into that much bigger problem of strengthening the cult of innocence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today we are observing Truth and Reconciliation Day, including in the second hour. I’ve heard this cult of innocence come up in conversations around that, too. It usually goes something like “those who committed the atrocities of the residential schools thought they were doing a good thing.” And it’s probably true that a lot of them did, because they subscribed to this cult of innocence where obviously they were superior and had to enforce their ways on others who are inferior. But when we say that as an excuse, a way to look away from the atrocities, we are refusing to acknowledge the harms done. We are setting up ourselves to do similar harms out of our own cult of innocence. We haven’t addressed the root of the problem being our sense of superiority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s the kind of scenario where this language about needing to cut off a part of the church body might come into play. It is cutting off the part of the church that might allow abuse. It is cutting off the pursuit of power over and against others. It is cutting off the superiority of my group over their group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Mark text feels like a strict binary. That’s not unusual for rabbis in that time to talk in hyperbole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In practice, all of this can get messier. It isn’t always clear what constitutes abuses of power and what is a difference of opinion about some complicated moral question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there is some bad history, for Mennonites and elsewhere, of rushing to apply “the ban” or “church discipline” to way too many things, banning anybody who doesn’t fit the high standards of the community. This then creates the power structure in the other direction, with the church now the abuser of the person they’ve kicked out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To speak in very broad generalities, a lot of conservative churches today would err on that side, quick to cast out somebody who doesn’t follow all the rules sufficiently. A lot of liberal churches have the opposite problem, where they are afraid of standing up for anything in case they go too far and alienate somebody already in the community. In doing so they end up supporting an abusive status quo. I think that’s the idea at the end of the reading, about the salt losing its saltiness. If there isn’t some unique substance to a community that makes it safe for the oppressed, they might end up through passivity with the same result as the overly aggressive power-seeking community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;james-vision-of-community&quot;&gt;James’ Vision of Community&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was another text read today. Ultimately, I included this James reading instead of the Numbers text because I think it provides some needed balance. The emphasis in this one is on restoration, bringing somebody back into community, rather than cutting somebody or something off. Two things about this community are named:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They confess their sins together.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They pray together and sing together.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think those two components are a valuable part of this bigger discussion of how we retain our saltiness against this domination mentality, without falling into that mentality ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Confessing our sins together helps combat the cult of innocence. That quest for power, that desire to rule over others, needs that fuel of feeling superior. And when we instead have a culture of being able to admit when we’ve messed up, or the things we’re struggling with, and we’re working together to do better, it’s a lot harder for that cult of innocence to take hold. It’s hard to want to dominate others while having a true sense of your own weaknesses. Not in a shameful way, just an honest one.
Several years ago, we were doing a series on the Mennonite Confession of Faith. Apparently, I’m a glutton for punishment taking hard topics that nobody else wants to talk about. This week and next week are things like discipline and nationalism and Christian identity. That time I looked at the Confession of Faith and promptly signed up for the article on sin. After talking about confession and repentance in some more detail than I did today, Scott got up for the congregational prayer and jokingly asked if anybody wanted to make a big public confession. To be clear, that’s not what I’m talking about, except maybe if it is a case where you harmed the whole community then you might need to apologize to the whole community. But for the most part, I’m talking more about the kinds of things that were highlighted in the service a couple weeks ago around a horizontal caring community. Ideally there would be someone or a small group that you feel safe talking to about the things you’re struggling with, or the way you harmed somebody and are trying to make it better. And a big part of the work of a local church is fostering an environment where those kinds of relationships can form and include everybody.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other idea from the James text is praying together and singing together. These are both ways to build a sense of community and shared values, to align our priorities with each other, with wider Christian tradition, and with God. They help us define ourselves as ourselves in a positive way. We’re not primarily defined by being better than them. Instead: What are we for? What is the kind of community that we want to be? When you have a clear vision of what you are, not only who or what you are against, your attention is focused there in the centre instead of on the boundaries trying to police who is and who isn’t good enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few years ago, we had an exercise explicitly like this. We developed as a church a vision statement that in part says, “we continue to grow and learn as we seek to live Christ’s wisdom and peace in the world.” Over time I’ve grown to like that statement more and more. We have a clearly defined positive centre, Christ’s wisdom and peace, and we acknowledge that we won’t always get it right but will keep growing together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve been in an interesting time as a congregation for a few years, basically since soon after that statement. Covid stopped us from meeting in person for a year and a half. Some who used to be regulars never came back. Some are joining us online, for any of a few very good reasons, not just Covid. Then our pastor of many years left, and we had some time with an interim pastor arrangement. Then Thomas fully took over, which in some ways is a brand-new thing and in other ways is completely familiar. A lot of these kinds of transitional times a community is just trying to tread water, to keep the pieces from falling apart. And thank you to everybody who has put in so much time keeping the pieces from falling apart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But those transitional times also give an opportunity, a chance to zoom out a bit and ask how we want to define ourselves. Not just what we stand against, not some cult of innocence pride that at least we aren’t like those people, but what do we stand for. That tension is where I will pick up more next week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;books&quot;&gt;Books&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do I Stay Christian: A Guide for the Doubters, the Disappointed, and the Disillusioned&lt;/em&gt; by Brian McLaren. This is a very pastoral book taking an honest look at the concept of a Christian identity. It acknowledges a lot of very serious harms both past and present that would justifiably cause us to abandon the label. It also includes practical reasons why you may choose to keep the label despite those things, and then offers some suggestions on how to proceed either way. The main idea borrowed for this sermon was the cult of innocence. It will be used more in part two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How To Have an Enemy: Righteous Anger and the Work of Peace&lt;/em&gt; by Melissa Florer-Bixler, a Mennonite USA pastor. This is a great examination of how Jesus responded to very real enemies and taught us to do the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;God and Empire&lt;/em&gt; by John Dominic Crossan. This is a good overview of the Bible’s conflict between an imperial worldview and a bottom-up peace worldview. At risk of disagreeing with one of the greatest living New Testament scholars, I do think he puts Revelation in the wrong category, though, missing out on what many other scholars will point out are the nonviolent themes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;youtube-and-podcasts&quot;&gt;YouTube and Podcasts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://yalebiblestudy.org/podcast/&quot;&gt;Chapter, Verse, and Season from Yale Divinity School&lt;/a&gt;. This doesn’t tie a lot into the themes of this week, but I did reference it at the beginning. Since this sermon, they have now completed their 3-year trip through the lectionary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.homebrewedchristianty.com/category/podcast/&quot;&gt;Homebrewed Christianity&lt;/a&gt; has had a lot of episodes relevant here but I’ll highlight two for this half:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5J1q8iLvD08&quot;&gt;Do I Stay Christian? a conversation with Brian McLaren about his new book&lt;/a&gt;. This is the intro to a series with Brian about the book referenced above.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZWghx1E67Z8&quot;&gt;Baptizing America: How Mainline Protestants Helped Build Christian Nationalism&lt;/a&gt;. This conversation, related to a different book that I have not read, looks at how Christian nationalism has not always been a right-wing problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;deleted-scene-concentric-circles&quot;&gt;Deleted Scene - Concentric Circles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[This section was a late cut to keep it fitting within my time limit. It would have come in near the end.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building on the idea of a centred positive definition, not policing the boundaries, I’ve sometimes used a model from Greg Boyd and &lt;a href=&quot;https://whchurch.org/&quot;&gt;Woodland Hills Church&lt;/a&gt; in Minnesota that has concentric circles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the centre is the person of Jesus. That’s what matters most. If we’re still looking toward the person of Jesus, we’re still in the same tradition. Then there’s dogma, which is the kind of things that were defined as orthodox Christianity a long time ago in ecumenical councils and for the most part is still maintained. Then there’s doctrine, where the differences do often have practical implications but there’s a lot of room for disagreement. That might include things like whether you do infant or adult baptism. It matters, and it might even matter enough that you pick a church with that as a factor – it is hard if you are a strong believer in adult baptism and you’re in a church doing infant baptism, or vice versa – but it’s ultimately fine and maybe even good that there are both. Finally, there’s opinion, which can be interesting to talk about but doesn’t really matter in a lot of practical ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tripp Fuller, on his podcast Homebrewed Christianity, has told a story about a youth confirmation class he taught. He inherited it as a big dogma and doctrine list to work through. But he reworked it to be a series of experiments in doing the things Jesus taught. He told the youth to write out their big theological questions throughout the course and put them in a big fishbowl, visible at the front of the room, and he promised he would get around to answering them eventually. But then he kept stalling answering them until the end after doing all these experiments. Then when they got to the end, they found nobody was still asking questions like whether Gandhi is in Hell, because they had already tried praying for their enemies. Through that experiment, they felt like they learned what they needed to know about God’s position toward those who are different. They never needed to sit and study their denomination’s doctrinal statements to have an intellectual debate. It was clear because they focused on what mattered most first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were similar themes in a recent Canadian Mennonite article: &lt;a href=&quot;https://canadianmennonite.org/stories/big-tent-small-centre&quot;&gt;Big tent, small centre | Canadian Mennonite Magazine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>New Blog</title>
    <link href="https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/new-blog/" />
    <updated>2024-02-21T21:46:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/new-blog/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Many years ago I was a regular blogger. I was even one of the founding members of the MennoNerds network of bloggers and podcasters. But blogging largely faded out in the face of social media dominance, and I found myself wanting to focus the majority of my energy on my local church community rather than writing for the public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latter half of that is still true. The majority of my energy is for my local church, not here. And I definitely won&#39;t blog about every Christian controversy of the day the way that I used to. But I have found myself wanting a place to put some things, like sermons that I already prepared for that local church priority, or even some longer form thoughts that were initially shared on Bluesky or Mastodon that I want to also be somewhere more permanent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, here is the beginning of getting that to work. I&#39;ve got the same technical framework for it as &lt;a href=&quot;https://tech.ryanrobinson.ca&quot;&gt;my tech blog&lt;/a&gt;. I&#39;ve got a few drafts to finish up. And maybe if I really find some free time at some point, I&#39;ll even convert some of my old blogs that I still have in a WordPress backup to work here.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>