<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="pretty-atom-feed.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
  <title>Ryan Robinson Theology</title>
  <subtitle>Ryan Robinson writes about theology: God, the church, the world, and whatever else he feels like that day.</subtitle>
  <link href="https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/feed/feed.xml" rel="self" />
  <link href="https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/" />
  <updated>2025-01-02T21:46:00Z</updated>
  <id>https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Ryan Robinson</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>Empathetic Imagination</title>
    <link href="https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/empathetic-imagination/" />
    <updated>2025-01-02T21:46:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/empathetic-imagination/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I heard a phrase recently that has stuck with me: &amp;quot;empathetic imagination.&amp;quot;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;movies-and-empathetic-storytelling&quot;&gt;Movies and Empathetic Storytelling&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This was on a movie podcast, which might not seem like the most obvious spot for a line about empathy that stuck out to me like this. But this podcast, named tongue in cheek The Only Podcast About Movies, is primarily approaching movies from the question of what the movie wants to say about the world. Storytelling is powerful, with movies being one of our greatest mediums at the moment, and one particular way it is powerful is in building empathy for stories that are different than yours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the main reason why I do appreciate good TV and movies so much. I am also interested in technical excellence in directing or acting or effects or any number of other elements of a movie. But primarily, I am interested in movies that tell a good story about people who are different than me in some way learning and growing. I want a movie to help me imagine the world being a little bit different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s also, to jump to a different medium, whey I always play videogames with female characters and with non-human characters when given the choice. I&#39;m a human male in real life and the majority of stories are about people like me. It&#39;s a little bit boring to do that all the time. If I have a chance to try to see the world in a slightly different way, I want to take it. I&#39;m very confused by certain elements of gamer culture that opposes the very existence of female characters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;empathy-and-politics&quot;&gt;Empathy and Politics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The context for the empathetic imagination comment was after the US election, and one of the hosts was lamenting the lack of empathetic imagination that made the result possible. He found it extremely discouraging that so few people could imagine how their voting choices would hurt the most vulnerable around them. I think that&#39;s an important insight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carol Off, in her book &lt;em&gt;At A Loss For Words&lt;/em&gt;, tells a story about speaking to a member of one of Canada&#39;s &amp;quot;freedom convoys.&amp;quot; Off asked what &amp;quot;freedom&amp;quot; meant to this convoy member, who replied something about individual choices to do whatever she wanted. Off asked her about a common phrase, that &amp;quot;my freedom ends where your freedom begins&amp;quot; and the convoy member had no idea what to do with that. She couldn&#39;t understand the concept. Off goes on throughout the book about this fundamental clash through history and the present between those who see the goal as their freedom to hurt and rule over whoever they want, and those who see the goal as an equitable freedom inclusive of everyone.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s a lack of empathetic imagination, a total inability to comprehend that other humans exist and your actions will impact them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The peak time of COVID may have been an ultimate example of this. There was a brief window where it seemed like everyone was on the same page that we need to look after each other because a virus is fundamentally a social problem, especially one that spreads at a rate faster than one new infection per current infection as COVID does (much less so when a significant portion of the population is vaccinated). Then the backlash began, where a significant portion of the population made it clear that they were tired of caring about other people. They talked openly about sacrificing the elderly, disabled, and children for the sake of their &amp;quot;freedom&amp;quot; to go to a crowded bar or whatever else they wanted to do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just what is the right political approach to &amp;quot;freedoms&amp;quot; can be complicated. We don&#39;t want a government enforcing tyranny on individuals. But we do want a government that can help remind individuals that we aren&#39;t just individuals - that whether we like it or not, we are in this world and this political entity together. And most importantly, we want a government that is able to understand that one group exercising its freedom may be a taking away of freedom from others. It is never as simple as &amp;quot;freedom&amp;quot; for everyone vs &amp;quot;tyranny&amp;quot; for everyone. But I do think a fundamental requirement for a functional society is some empathetic imagination, letting us wrestle with some of those complicated moments while maintaining understanding of what it will mean to others, particularly those most marginalized. That fundamental requirement is currently lacking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;accessible-web-dev&quot;&gt;Accessible Web Dev&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One more tangent is to tie this idea into my day job, building websites.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My previous job was for a small company where I was primarily building small websites and CRM systems for non-profits. It&#39;s important work, I&#39;m glad somebody is doing it, and I still recommend the people there when I encounter someone that could use those services. But there is something inherent to that style of work, constantly bouncing between doing similar jobs for multiple clients as fast as possible in order to not lose money, that gets tiring. A chunk of that may be that there is no time to get deep on technical challenges, but even more I realized after starting my current job: there isn&#39;t any time for empathetic imagination. It&#39;s all about getting through the checklist as fast as possible. That includes when it comes to accessibility, which usually had a bare minimum checklist to clear with some automated tools.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the first big non-technical things I learned in my current job was working with a blind student consultant, who was able to walk some of us sighted staff through her experiences. Instead of &amp;quot;does this test fail&amp;quot; my question became a lot more of &amp;quot;how does her experience compare to a sighted experience? Is there more we can do to make that equal?&amp;quot; That&#39;s a radically different way of thinking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blind users may be the biggest focus of website accessibility; since websites are primarily visible, that&#39;s the group most consistently left out if the site is not built well. But that&#39;s not the only group to consider. What if you&#39;re deaf and encounter a video with sound? What if you&#39;re colour-blind, or have low vision? What if you&#39;re brand new to the subject of the site with no knowledge of the jargon, vs those who know exactly what they&#39;re looking for?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I write about some of those more on my tech blog and won&#39;t repeat it all here, but I did want to tie it into the idea of empathetic imagination. I am routinely needing to imagine the experiences of others. It makes me a better developer, and I think it makes me a better person.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Shiphrah, Puah, and Moses</title>
    <link href="https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/shiphrah-puah-moses/" />
    <updated>2024-12-10T19:04:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/shiphrah-puah-moses/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I occasionally think about the contrast of the first two chapters of Exodus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In chapter 1, Shiphrah and Puah were midwives who were ordered to kill Hebrew babies. But they don&#39;t do it, instead claiming Hebrew women gave birth before they could get there. They undermined the system, saving a lot of lives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In chapter 2, Moses, raised in palace privilege because of a different bit of quiet courage from another couple women, sees a slaver beating a Hebrew. He gets mad, kills him, then has to go into hiding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The role of privilege here does matter, I think. Moses grew up in the palace. He has probably always been taught that the way to enact change is to wield your strength against those who need to be kept in line. So when he sees an Egyptian beating a Hebrew and gets angry, that&#39;s how he responds: wielding his power violently. Then he is surprised to learn that the Hebrew slaves were not excited by this display of dominance; they are afraid that he&#39;ll do the same to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course Moses eventually becomes the movie-style hero that is the symbol of the Exodus. But first he has to spend an entire generation in exile, surrendering the privilege and domination mindset he had, encountering God, and waiting for the people who were trying to kill him to die off. And in that time, &amp;quot;the Israelites were still groaning&amp;quot; (CEB) in slavery, who maybe could have been helped if he shown some wisdom earlier.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I recently watched the first Hobbit movie again, and was struck by this bit of Tolkien wisdom about power:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saruman believes that it is only great power that can hold evil in check. But that is not what I have found. I&#39;ve found it is the small things, everyday deeds of ordinary folk that keeps the darkness at bay. Simple acts of kindness and love.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&#39;s at least one big difference from the Exodus context, and the Hobbit context, compared to my context and likely the context of most readers: unlike Egypt at this time, we live in a democracy. We have more ability to directly oppose evil with freedom of expression. And we definitely need a lot of people in that category, explicitly countering harm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I think we also need the Shiphrahs and the Puahs, those who will quietly throw a stick into the gears of the death machine, saving a lot of lives in the process even if nobody seems to notice.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Preaching</title>
    <link href="https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/preaching/" />
    <updated>2024-12-08T11:46:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/preaching/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I recently joined &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newleafnetwork.ca/store/postevangelicalpreaching&quot;&gt;a New Leaf Network class on Preaching in a Post-Evangelical World&lt;/a&gt;. I only preach 1-2 times a year, and in &lt;a href=&quot;https://rockwaymc.ca&quot;&gt;a church&lt;/a&gt; that would not typically be described as post-evangelical or any other kind of evangelical, but I still find the topic very interesting and I anticipated correctly that they would still be talking through some relevant questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&#39;m not going to recap everything they talked about, but will use it as a launching pad to touch on some of the main considerations I have when I am preaching:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;audience-context&quot;&gt;Audience Context&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They talk a lot in the New Leaf class about knowing your audience context. What you say to a mostly privileged church needs to be very different than what you say to a poorer, less educated, or otherwise oppressed church. My church? It&#39;s mostly privileged: not quite all white most weeks, mostly pretty solidly middle class, highly educated, mostly cis and straight, mostly married, mostly able-bodied, average age probably in their 60s. I am also mostly privileged. When I preach at my church, I am speaking from that perspective, as somebody wrestling with using my own privilege well and trying to help others do the same. So I do end up talking about things like systemic racism, or more broadly the need to acknowledge our sin. I wouldn&#39;t do that, or at least not in nearly the same way, with a majority Black or poor church. They know the world is broken; they experience it every day. They don&#39;t need that spoken to them. They probably need a lot more of a reminder of how God is with them in that oppression and we have hope that God will bring justice in all the practical ways to restore them as equal members of society.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the weird parts of considering audience context is being published widely to the Internet. When I write something to say, I&#39;m writing it for my context. A lot of others share that context, and I hope if they stumble across it on this site or the church&#39;s site or YouTube that it will help them, and I do believe strongly that in almost all circumstances a church&#39;s sermons should be available publicly as an entry point for somebody wanting to check it out and learn more about the community. But it does also mean others with very different contexts can find it and it might be the exact opposite message of what they need to hear right now. That can be mediated a little by making my context as clear as I can, but it will always be true that one message can&#39;t be perfect for everyone in all contexts at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;expository-preaching&quot;&gt;Expository Preaching&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the New Leaf class, they talk about expository as the default approach to preaching in evangelical circles. This approach that is very much focused on walking through the text, helping explain it generally in the order it appears, as opposed to a more topical approach that starts from a current relevant question. It has some big advantages mainly that it keeps the text a little more in its context.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I skew a little more expository than most in my church, but still not a lot compared to a lot of evangelicals. I mostly think it&#39;s hard to do really well in a meaningful way in a 15-20 sermon slot, at least not without being part of a longer series or being connected to Adult Education for more help. There just isn&#39;t time to go really deep into Scriptural context. There are exceptions: the first in my recent double header was much more expository, and I will have the final piece of a series on Ephesians that will likely end up a bit more expository. The New Leaf session touches on some of the problem with expository as well, that it often ends up arrogantly projecting what we want into the text, while pretending we&#39;re letting it speak for itself, because we do have a social context which does impact our reading whether we like to admit it or not. There is really no such thing as &amp;quot;letting the text speak for itself&amp;quot;; we&#39;re always interpreting. But if you&#39;re able to still come in with that honesty about your perspective, then yes, I think it is valuable to have some sermons that start from the text and some that start from the topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;is-it-antiquated&quot;&gt;Is It Antiquated?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;New Leaf&#39;s class raises the point that a lot of people think of preaching as an antiquated form. Having one person speak and others listen is not a very good way to learn. So why do we still do it? Several years ago, one member of our church preached on why he preached, and he essentially said that while only hearing something is bad for learning it, formulating your thoughts enough to be able to preach it is a very good way to learn or wrestle with something. So preaching is good for the preacher at least, if they&#39;re being honest in their wrestling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That is close to what I&#39;m often going for now when I preach: I want to model wrestling with the Scripture text and our tradition and our current world, and invite others into that wrestling. They don&#39;t have to conclude the same on whatever topic as I do. I don&#39;t care about that. But I do care that they are called into the kind of community that is willing to wrestle through the hard parts of life together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s also where I see the difference in preaching and teaching. Teaching is a fairly intellectual lecture or discussion getting deep into a specific issue, and in our church the Adult Education hour does that more. Preaching is more about inviting each other into a community around Jesus. That requires a lot more humility than the approach where the preacher is declaring God&#39;s perfect truth, and it probably takes more of a community where preaching duties are more shared in order to avoid only hearing one voice, but it&#39;s much more powerful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-role-of-the-sermon&quot;&gt;The Role of the Sermon&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the sermon is valuable, but it probably shouldn&#39;t be the absolute only thing that matters. I&#39;m a big proponent on doing the Eucharist/communion regularly, that embodied act of remembering the Jesus story together in an extremely tangible way. I personally do not care as much about music, but I know a lot do. I&#39;m also a big fan of communal prayer, sharing our thanks and requests together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think sermons are often important, especially as an entry point for somebody who is new. It is the most opportunity to clearly convey what the community thinks this whole Jesus thing is about, and we live in a world where a lot of people no longer have any idea what this Jesus thing is about. So I especially want to preserve the sermon on days like Easter or leading up to Christmas, when people are most likely to come for the first time, or the first time in a while.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That doesn&#39;t necessarily mean it has to be the central feature of every service. It doesn&#39;t even mean that it has to be present in every service. On the opposite end from Easter may be something like Thanksgiving, at least in our church: a lot of people are away, and if they are there they are likely tired juggling family commitments, there is highly unlikely to be anybody new showing up, and while gratitude broadly is certainly coherent with Christianity Thanksgiving is not a specifically Christian holiday. So that day, our church usually doesn&#39;t have a sermon, instead replacing it with a day of singing and poems. It allows for a more meditative space, which is a valuable change of pace.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Hope is a Sewer Rat</title>
    <link href="https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/hope-sewer-rat/" />
    <updated>2024-12-07T21:46:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/hope-sewer-rat/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I love this poem I&#39;ve seen go around social media a couple of times, called Hope is a Sewer Rat by Caitlin Seida.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hope is not the thing with feathers
That comes home to roost
When you need it most.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hope is an ugly thing
With teeth and claws and
Patchy fur that’s seen some shit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s what thrives in the discards
And survives in the ugliest parts of our world,
Able to find a way to go on
When nothing else can even find a way in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s the gritty, nasty little carrier of such
diseases as
optimism, persistence,
Perseverance and joy,
Transmissible as it drags its tail across
your path
and
bites you in the ass.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hope is not some delicate, beautiful bird,
Emily.
It’s a lowly little sewer rat
That snorts pesticides like they were
Lines of coke and still
Shows up on time to work the next day
Looking no worse for wear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe sometimes hope actually is the delicate bird that arrives just when you need it and reminds you of a better world. I&#39;m not ruling that out. But a lot of the time, yeah, I think it&#39;s the sewer rat, something that gets beat up by the world over and over again and yet, if we choose to, it comes back for more.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>AMBS: Challenging Christian Nationalism</title>
    <link href="https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/ambs-challenging-christian-nationalism/" />
    <updated>2024-11-24T21:46:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/ambs-challenging-christian-nationalism/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;See below for a great presentation at Anabaptist Mennonite Biblical Seminary about Christian Nationalism. This was before the US election, but it&#39;s no less relevant now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ubCYHYa0KKM?si=cK3CyuLnMfLa4znX&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; referrerpolicy=&quot;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This has a lot of similar themes to my recent pair of sermons which I will hopefully be posting soon, but obviously it is longer and much more academic, getting into more precise details of movements in the US.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>To Remember Is To Work for Peace</title>
    <link href="https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/remembrance-day/" />
    <updated>2024-11-11T21:46:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/remembrance-day/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Remembrance Day often carries two different tones with it:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;War is horrible. We honour those who died by grieving that horror with all its lost lives.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;War is super important and we need our national team to win, so support our troops and cheer when they do more violence than the other side does.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anabaptists like myself are mostly ok with the first part. We hold in high esteem those who would sacrifice their lives for others. The only real question is how many soldiers really choose to sacrifice their lives, rather than being pushed to by nationalist forces who stand to gain. If it isn&#39;t chosen then it isn&#39;t really a sacrifice on their part. It is often more accurate to say that some politicians and war profiteers sacrificed those soldiers&#39; lives for their profit. But I digress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&#39;s the second part that we start to have a problem with Remembrance Day. Anabaptists remain firm that our loyalty is to Jesus, not to any nation, and Jesus is pretty clear about the whole nonviolent love of enemies thing. So grieving violence makes complete sense. The nationalist jingoism, the cheerleading of violence as long as it is against THEM instead of against US, does not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For several years, Mennonites have often worn a red pin that says &amp;quot;To remember is to work for peace.&amp;quot; That might be in addition to the poppy (if we&#39;re focusing more on the first part above) or instead of (if we&#39;re focusing more on the second part). Either way, this is the most essential part in my worldview: if you truly grieve wars and violence more generally, if you truly want to remember and honour those who died, you will want to work to keep that from happening again whether that&#39;s in Ukraine or Canada or Palestine or anywhere else. Being a peacemaker is not a simple opting out of violence; it must be an active work toward a more just and whole world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&#39;s my quick reflection of the day. Here&#39;s Marlene Epp speaking at my church, Rockway Mennonite, about some of the history of Mennonites with Remembrance Day:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/drsv8C1PFk0?si=lhG0xUPctLHa-XUk&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; referrerpolicy=&quot;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>The Cult of Innocence</title>
    <link href="https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/cult-innocence/" />
    <updated>2024-09-29T21:46:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/cult-innocence/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;This was the first of what turned into a two-part sermon recently.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;scripture-texts&quot;&gt;Scripture Texts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the lectionary for that day: &lt;a href=&quot;https://bibles.org/bible/1fd99b0d5841e19b-02/JAS.5?passageId=JAS.5.13-JAS.5.20&amp;amp;q=james%205%3A13-20&quot;&gt;James 5:13-20&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://bibles.org/bible/1fd99b0d5841e19b-02/MRK.9?passageId=MRK.9.38-MRK.9.47&amp;amp;q=mark%209%3A38-50&quot;&gt;Mark 9:38-50&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;video&quot;&gt;Video&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&#39;s the video version from the church&#39;s YouTube:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/LQmA_RiR1xk?si=dEqQSImZTuK2nV3V&quot; title=&quot;YouTube video player&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&quot; referrerpolicy=&quot;strict-origin-when-cross-origin&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;transcript&quot;&gt;Transcript&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The transcript is cleaned up a little to be more general and shareable to the wider public. I also always end up improvising a little when I speak, so what is written down is not exactly the same as what would be captions on the video.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“There’s a lot of weirdness in this text.” That was the opening line of a podcast episode from Yale Divinity where they look at a passage from the lectionary briefly each week, including this week’s Mark text. Yeah, I think that’s a pretty good assessment. Most of it is very familiar if you’ve been around the church for long. But that doesn’t make it that much less weird. There is a lot that feels like non-sequiturs, jumping between loosely related ideas, and in my experience most sermons using it end up picking a specific part to zone in on rather than trying to treat it as one whole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I first read it in preparation for today, the first section is what I zoned in on. I started with the punchline “whoever is not against us is with us.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was also &lt;a href=&quot;https://bibles.org/bible/1fd99b0d5841e19b-02/NUM.11?passageId=NUM.11.4-NUM.11.13&amp;amp;q=numbers%2011%3A4-29&quot;&gt;a Numbers text in the lectionary for today, chapter 11:4-29&lt;/a&gt;, which has a parallel story. As the disciples do with Jesus in Mark, Moses’ assistant Joshua comes to Moses and tells Moses to stop a couple people from prophesying. Like Jesus in the Mark story, Moses doesn’t see it as a problem at all, instead glad that others are also doing good work, and warns Joshua not to be jealous for his sake.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There’s a good lesson there about celebrating those who are acting in line with our values, even if they aren’t active in our church or any church.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That was it. That was the whole original sermon idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But unfortunately for those of you think sermons are too long, I kept thinking about these texts. And I kept thinking about the general state of Christianity in North America. And I kept coming across books and podcasts that seemed to have relevant things to say. In fact, I kept thinking about them enough that, in combination with some needed juggling of the worship schedule, this changed from one sermon into two. I will also be speaking again next week, continuing where I leave off today but from a slightly different direction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;power-and-christian-institution&quot;&gt;Power and Christian Institution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, I looked at more context of the Mark passage to try to connect some of those seemingly disconnected pieces. Sometimes it&#39;s easy when we mostly encounter the Bible in these little segments to forget that these stories were pieced together the way they were for a reason. The Bible didn’t originally have the section headers we have now; those are put in by modern translators and don’t even always agree with each other. It didn’t even have chapter and verse numbers for a long time, or for that matter, even punctuation in the original Greek. Mark was just one long book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I found that the section before the lectionary text is helpful for some framing. There, Jesus says that he will be killed and then rise again. The disciples don’t get it. So of course, they don’t ask any follow-up questions, which is a great way to continue to not get it. Then the disciples were debating with each other about who is the greatest. Jesus tells them that whoever wants to be first must be least of all, then calls in a nearby child to emphasize the point: whoever welcomes one of these children in his name welcomes him. That is some of our thematic context: the disciples are trying to position themselves to be near the top of the Jesus follower hierarchy. Jesus tries to teach them to reverse their thinking to prioritize the marginalized, particularly in this case, children.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With that in mind, I think a lot of that conflict is carrying forward into today’s text. We see that the disciples were not upset with what this other person was doing, the casting out demons part. They weren’t even upset with his attitude doing it. They say that he was doing it in Jesus’ name. That phrase is easy for us to read as if the name Jesus or Christ or Christian is a magic word. That is often how it gets used today. Sometimes if we’re being honest, when we end a prayer with “in Jesus’ name”, we’re probably thinking of it like a magic word, thinking that makes it more likely that we’ll get what we want. But also more to the point here, it is often used as a magic word by others like politicians and online social influencers. In that context, it is used to manufacture consent by meaning things like “we’re the good guys, you should vote for us, and you definitely shouldn’t be upset about all the terrible things we are doing because we are CHRISTIANS and that is all that matters!” I’m going to be talking about them more directly next week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But in that cultural context, the phrasing “in the name of” means more like “a representative of.” If you do something in the name of the king, you’re saying that you’re doing what the king wanted you to do. A modern twist on that might be “don’t shoot the messenger.” If the messenger is relaying what somebody with higher authority told them to do, and you don’t like the message, the person you’re really upset with is the higher authority, not the messenger. So when the disciples are saying that this exorcist is doing it in Jesus’ name, they probably mean that he was doing it in a way consistent with Jesus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The disciples acknowledged that this exorcist was doing a good thing for the right reasons, but were upset “because he wasn’t following us.” He’s outside of their perceived in-group, outside their desired power structure. And like the previous passage, Jesus again conveys that they’ve missed the point and need to flip their concept of power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re talking about two groups. There are people in the Jesus institution – for lack of a better word - doing good work, and people who are inspired by Jesus but not part of the institution also doing good work. Obviously, there are a lot of other groups in the world, some of which I’ll talk about more in part two next week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the modern world, that latter group is often those who decided they couldn’t put up with all the problems of the church but are still compelled by Jesus in some way. This is a substantial group, mainly because the church has messed up a lot. There’s a lot of reasons why people might have problems with Christianity. Even within the themes of hierarchy and power, there is a lot to work with, past and present. Crusades and witch hunts and inquisitions and colonialism and residential school and many aspects of the current wave of Christian nationalism, and on and on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This quest for power, in both the disciples and the modern church, is usually backed up by what Brian McLaren calls a cult of innocence, in his book &lt;em&gt;Do I Stay Christian&lt;/em&gt;. To justify that your group should rule over others, you need to believe that your group is the correct pure group, and those others are evil that must be punished, or at least inferior that must be controlled.
And it is really easy for me to hear that and think “yeah, I’m so glad I don’t have that attitude like some other people. I’m so glad that I am one of the good guys. I’m never judgemental like those bad guys! We have to find a way to stop them!” And then I realize that I just did my own cult of innocence thinking. It’s a human temptation, not unique to some other group of people we don’t like. It’s one that we aren’t immune to, and the more we think we’re immune to it the more likely we are to fall into it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;cutting-it-off&quot;&gt;Cutting It Off&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That brings us back to the second part of the Mark text. In my experience, a lot of the time I have heard this passage quoted started at verse 43: if your hand causes you to sin, cut it off, and so on. I think I heard that a lot as a teenager and young adult being on the fringes of the purity culture movement. I wasn’t getting nearly the worst of it as my church was pretty good, but I got some tangentially especially as the Internet became a thing. It was used to sell things like monitoring software on your computer to make sure you weren’t accessing pornography. The text was interpreted that you should cut off the ways that you individually sin – and of course the only real sins worth talking about are the sexual ones. And I don’t want to completely squash the general idea there. There is some wisdom in identifying your weak points and having the self-control to avoid them. But also, the extreme focus on sex was bad, and even the better more general version is maybe missing some context here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The context for Mark here is somebody who has harmed a child, or in an interesting bit of phrasing, has caused a child to sin. In that case, the thing that we’re talking about needing to be cut off might be more about harmful power structures and the attitudes that support them within our community, not about individual computer access. They need to be cut off before they become engrained in children, causing them to then continue the cycles of violence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For me, this is where the cult of innocence attitude jumps in again. See, this text tells me to cut off those terrible Christian nationalists! They are obviously harming the marginalized and amplifying these cycles of violence. I should spend all my free time on the Internet making sure to tell strangers about how those aren’t real Christians, not like I am!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then I check myself again. For one, arguing with strangers on the Internet is mostly counterproductive. But I think more importantly, it leads into that much bigger problem of strengthening the cult of innocence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today we are observing Truth and Reconciliation Day, including in the second hour. I’ve heard this cult of innocence come up in conversations around that, too. It usually goes something like “those who committed the atrocities of the residential schools thought they were doing a good thing.” And it’s probably true that a lot of them did, because they subscribed to this cult of innocence where obviously they were superior and had to enforce their ways on others who are inferior. But when we say that as an excuse, a way to look away from the atrocities, we are refusing to acknowledge the harms done. We are setting up ourselves to do similar harms out of our own cult of innocence. We haven’t addressed the root of the problem being our sense of superiority.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s the kind of scenario where this language about needing to cut off a part of the church body might come into play. It is cutting off the part of the church that might allow abuse. It is cutting off the pursuit of power over and against others. It is cutting off the superiority of my group over their group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Mark text feels like a strict binary. That’s not unusual for rabbis in that time to talk in hyperbole.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In practice, all of this can get messier. It isn’t always clear what constitutes abuses of power and what is a difference of opinion about some complicated moral question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there is some bad history, for Mennonites and elsewhere, of rushing to apply “the ban” or “church discipline” to way too many things, banning anybody who doesn’t fit the high standards of the community. This then creates the power structure in the other direction, with the church now the abuser of the person they’ve kicked out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To speak in very broad generalities, a lot of conservative churches today would err on that side, quick to cast out somebody who doesn’t follow all the rules sufficiently. A lot of liberal churches have the opposite problem, where they are afraid of standing up for anything in case they go too far and alienate somebody already in the community. In doing so they end up supporting an abusive status quo. I think that’s the idea at the end of the reading, about the salt losing its saltiness. If there isn’t some unique substance to a community that makes it safe for the oppressed, they might end up through passivity with the same result as the overly aggressive power-seeking community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;james-vision-of-community&quot;&gt;James’ Vision of Community&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There was another text read today. Ultimately, I included this James reading instead of the Numbers text because I think it provides some needed balance. The emphasis in this one is on restoration, bringing somebody back into community, rather than cutting somebody or something off. Two things about this community are named:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They confess their sins together.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;They pray together and sing together.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I think those two components are a valuable part of this bigger discussion of how we retain our saltiness against this domination mentality, without falling into that mentality ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Confessing our sins together helps combat the cult of innocence. That quest for power, that desire to rule over others, needs that fuel of feeling superior. And when we instead have a culture of being able to admit when we’ve messed up, or the things we’re struggling with, and we’re working together to do better, it’s a lot harder for that cult of innocence to take hold. It’s hard to want to dominate others while having a true sense of your own weaknesses. Not in a shameful way, just an honest one.
Several years ago, we were doing a series on the Mennonite Confession of Faith. Apparently, I’m a glutton for punishment taking hard topics that nobody else wants to talk about. This week and next week are things like discipline and nationalism and Christian identity. That time I looked at the Confession of Faith and promptly signed up for the article on sin. After talking about confession and repentance in some more detail than I did today, Scott got up for the congregational prayer and jokingly asked if anybody wanted to make a big public confession. To be clear, that’s not what I’m talking about, except maybe if it is a case where you harmed the whole community then you might need to apologize to the whole community. But for the most part, I’m talking more about the kinds of things that were highlighted in the service a couple weeks ago around a horizontal caring community. Ideally there would be someone or a small group that you feel safe talking to about the things you’re struggling with, or the way you harmed somebody and are trying to make it better. And a big part of the work of a local church is fostering an environment where those kinds of relationships can form and include everybody.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other idea from the James text is praying together and singing together. These are both ways to build a sense of community and shared values, to align our priorities with each other, with wider Christian tradition, and with God. They help us define ourselves as ourselves in a positive way. We’re not primarily defined by being better than them. Instead: What are we for? What is the kind of community that we want to be? When you have a clear vision of what you are, not only who or what you are against, your attention is focused there in the centre instead of on the boundaries trying to police who is and who isn’t good enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few years ago, we had an exercise explicitly like this. We developed as a church a vision statement that in part says, “we continue to grow and learn as we seek to live Christ’s wisdom and peace in the world.” Over time I’ve grown to like that statement more and more. We have a clearly defined positive centre, Christ’s wisdom and peace, and we acknowledge that we won’t always get it right but will keep growing together.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve been in an interesting time as a congregation for a few years, basically since soon after that statement. Covid stopped us from meeting in person for a year and a half. Some who used to be regulars never came back. Some are joining us online, for any of a few very good reasons, not just Covid. Then our pastor of many years left, and we had some time with an interim pastor arrangement. Then Thomas fully took over, which in some ways is a brand-new thing and in other ways is completely familiar. A lot of these kinds of transitional times a community is just trying to tread water, to keep the pieces from falling apart. And thank you to everybody who has put in so much time keeping the pieces from falling apart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But those transitional times also give an opportunity, a chance to zoom out a bit and ask how we want to define ourselves. Not just what we stand against, not some cult of innocence pride that at least we aren’t like those people, but what do we stand for. That tension is where I will pick up more next week.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;resources&quot;&gt;Resources&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;books&quot;&gt;Books&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do I Stay Christian: A Guide for the Doubters, the Disappointed, and the Disillusioned&lt;/em&gt; by Brian McLaren. This is a very pastoral book taking an honest look at the concept of a Christian identity. It acknowledges a lot of very serious harms both past and present that would justifiably cause us to abandon the label. It also includes practical reasons why you may choose to keep the label despite those things, and then offers some suggestions on how to proceed either way. The main idea borrowed for this sermon was the cult of innocence. It will be used more in part two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How To Have an Enemy: Righteous Anger and the Work of Peace&lt;/em&gt; by Melissa Florer-Bixler, a Mennonite USA pastor. This is a great examination of how Jesus responded to very real enemies and taught us to do the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;God and Empire&lt;/em&gt; by John Dominic Crossan. This is a good overview of the Bible’s conflict between an imperial worldview and a bottom-up peace worldview. At risk of disagreeing with one of the greatest living New Testament scholars, I do think he puts Revelation in the wrong category, though, missing out on what many other scholars will point out are the nonviolent themes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;youtube-and-podcasts&quot;&gt;YouTube and Podcasts&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://yalebiblestudy.org/podcast/&quot;&gt;Chapter, Verse, and Season from Yale Divinity School&lt;/a&gt;. This doesn’t tie a lot into the themes of this week, but I did reference it at the beginning. Since this sermon, they have now completed their 3-year trip through the lectionary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.homebrewedchristianty.com/category/podcast/&quot;&gt;Homebrewed Christianity&lt;/a&gt; has had a lot of episodes relevant here but I’ll highlight two for this half:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=5J1q8iLvD08&quot;&gt;Do I Stay Christian? a conversation with Brian McLaren about his new book&lt;/a&gt;. This is the intro to a series with Brian about the book referenced above.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ZWghx1E67Z8&quot;&gt;Baptizing America: How Mainline Protestants Helped Build Christian Nationalism&lt;/a&gt;. This conversation, related to a different book that I have not read, looks at how Christian nationalism has not always been a right-wing problem.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;deleted-scene-concentric-circles&quot;&gt;Deleted Scene - Concentric Circles&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[This section was a late cut to keep it fitting within my time limit. It would have come in near the end.]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Building on the idea of a centred positive definition, not policing the boundaries, I’ve sometimes used a model from Greg Boyd and &lt;a href=&quot;https://whchurch.org/&quot;&gt;Woodland Hills Church&lt;/a&gt; in Minnesota that has concentric circles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the centre is the person of Jesus. That’s what matters most. If we’re still looking toward the person of Jesus, we’re still in the same tradition. Then there’s dogma, which is the kind of things that were defined as orthodox Christianity a long time ago in ecumenical councils and for the most part is still maintained. Then there’s doctrine, where the differences do often have practical implications but there’s a lot of room for disagreement. That might include things like whether you do infant or adult baptism. It matters, and it might even matter enough that you pick a church with that as a factor – it is hard if you are a strong believer in adult baptism and you’re in a church doing infant baptism, or vice versa – but it’s ultimately fine and maybe even good that there are both. Finally, there’s opinion, which can be interesting to talk about but doesn’t really matter in a lot of practical ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tripp Fuller, on his podcast Homebrewed Christianity, has told a story about a youth confirmation class he taught. He inherited it as a big dogma and doctrine list to work through. But he reworked it to be a series of experiments in doing the things Jesus taught. He told the youth to write out their big theological questions throughout the course and put them in a big fishbowl, visible at the front of the room, and he promised he would get around to answering them eventually. But then he kept stalling answering them until the end after doing all these experiments. Then when they got to the end, they found nobody was still asking questions like whether Gandhi is in Hell, because they had already tried praying for their enemies. Through that experiment, they felt like they learned what they needed to know about God’s position toward those who are different. They never needed to sit and study their denomination’s doctrinal statements to have an intellectual debate. It was clear because they focused on what mattered most first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There were similar themes in a recent Canadian Mennonite article: &lt;a href=&quot;https://canadianmennonite.org/stories/big-tent-small-centre&quot;&gt;Big tent, small centre | Canadian Mennonite Magazine&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>New Blog</title>
    <link href="https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/new-blog/" />
    <updated>2024-02-21T21:46:00Z</updated>
    <id>https://theology.ryanrobinson.ca/posts/2024/new-blog/</id>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Many years ago I was a regular blogger. I was even one of the founding members of the MennoNerds network of bloggers and podcasters. But blogging largely faded out in the face of social media dominance, and I found myself wanting to focus the majority of my energy on my local church community rather than writing for the public.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The latter half of that is still true. The majority of my energy is for my local church, not here. And I definitely won&#39;t blog about every Christian controversy of the day the way that I used to. But I have found myself wanting a place to put some things, like sermons that I already prepared for that local church priority, or even some longer form thoughts that were initially shared on Bluesky or Mastodon that I want to also be somewhere more permanent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, here is the beginning of getting that to work. I&#39;ve got the same technical framework for it as &lt;a href=&quot;https://tech.ryanrobinson.ca&quot;&gt;my tech blog&lt;/a&gt;. I&#39;ve got a few drafts to finish up. And maybe if I really find some free time at some point, I&#39;ll even convert some of my old blogs that I still have in a WordPress backup to work here.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>